<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God, the King, and the countrey, united in the justification of this present revolution containing also animadversions on Dr. William Sherlock's book intituled, The case of allegiance due to soveraign powers, stated and resolved, according to scripture and reason, and the principles of the Church and England / by Tim. Wilson ...</title>
            <author>Wilson, Timothy, 1642-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8407</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924273</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12924273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95438</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95438)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 991:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God, the King, and the countrey, united in the justification of this present revolution containing also animadversions on Dr. William Sherlock's book intituled, The case of allegiance due to soveraign powers, stated and resolved, according to scripture and reason, and the principles of the Church and England / by Tim. Wilson ...</title>
                  <author>Wilson, Timothy, 1642-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Case of the allegiance due to soveraign powers.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95438:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95438:1"/>
            <p>GOD, THE KING, AND THE COUNTREY, United in the Juſtification of this <hi>Preſent Revolution:</hi> Containing alſo Animadverſions on Dr. William Sherlock's Book; Intituled, <hi>The Caſe of Allegiance Due to Soveraign Powers, ſtated and reſolved, according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon; and the Principles of the Church of</hi> England. By <hi>TIM. WILSON,</hi> M. A. and Rector of <hi>Great Mongeham</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Licenſed, <hi>Jan.</hi> 29. 1691.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel. 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95438:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95438:2"/>
            <head>To the Sacred Majeſties of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> by the Grace of God King and Queen of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defenders of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſties,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Divine Providence, that diſpoſeth all things to the emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lument and advantage of thoſe that love God, hath ſent Your Majeſties to be our Saviours and Deliverers from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Slavery, to the Joy of all ſound Proteſtants, not wholly ſunk and buried in prejudice. And we ſee the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> fulfilled, <hi>Kings ſhall be your Nurſing Fathers, and Queens your Nurſing Mothers.</hi> But the Government of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom God ſent into <hi>Egypt</hi> to deliver his people, was not without ſome Murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and men of a revolting ſpirit, who looked back towards <hi>Egypt.</hi> Victorious <hi>David</hi> had that crafty Politician, <hi>Achitophel,</hi> his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary; and <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who ſtole away the hearts of this people; and <hi>Sheba,</hi> a Mover of Sedition. The Reign of <hi>Solomon</hi> had ſome, who complained of Grievances and Oppreſſions, tho' he honoured God by building a Magnificent Temple. The moſt excellent <hi>Deborah,</hi> tho' ſhe had ſome that jeoparded their lives unto death with her, yet ſhe had others, who for their Diviſions cauſed great thoughts of heart. It is my affection to the Proteſtant Cauſe, and Your Majeſties Government, that moves me thus reſolutely to ruſh into your Sacred Preſence. I am very ſenſible that falſe Principles will create Practices correſpondent to them: And therefore I have examined ſome new and ſtrange No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gods Providence, and Humane Governments of late aſſerted by ſome Doctors. To ſay, <hi>That a Prince hath Gods Authority, tho' he hath no Humane and Legal Right, and that there is another Perſon, who hath Legal Right, is diſmal to conſider in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences thereof.</hi> If this Poiſon creeps into the Church, I tremble to reflect upon the Effects of it. It is good for nothing but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Inſincerity, and to make men ſwear to live peaceably, when
<pb facs="tcp:95438:3"/>they have War in their hearts. I am confident of Your Majeſties Protection; for I have acted in this Affair with a full ſatisfaction of Conſcience, and the greateſt Evidence of Reaſon. And no Hiſtory can exceed, if parallel, ſo great valour and courage, mixed with ſo much grace and clemency, as hath ſhined in King <hi>William.</hi> This is to be like God, who is Almighty, and yet ſlow to wrath; whoſe Power is irreſiſtible, and yet he delights in Mercy. Go on, and proſper, moſt victorious Prince; and may the God of Heaven bleſs you with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs by Sea and Land againſt that proud and perſecuting Monarch, who hath been the Ruine of ſo many Innocent Proteſtants in his own Dominions. May God give Your Majeſties the Necks of your Enemies, and may they all taſt of Your Forgiveneſs and Bounty, but never forſake Your firſt Friends, who ran all hazards with Your Majeſty. I pray with <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who ſaith, We Chriſtians pray for our Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; <hi>1.</hi> That they may have a long Life; which contains Health, Joy and Proſperity. <hi>2.</hi> A conſtant, ſafe and ſecure Government. <hi>3.</hi> Faithful and Truſty Domeſtick Servants, free from Treachery, and ſecret Conſpiracy. <hi>4.</hi> A ſtrong and valiant Army. <hi>5.</hi> A faithful Senate, Council, or Parliament. <hi>6.</hi> Obedient, Submiſſive and Loyal People. <hi>7.</hi> A quiet and peaceable Reign. In a word, whatſoever can be the deſire of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God inſpire Your Majeſties with heavenly Grace and Wiſdom, and ſound Knowledge, and good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding to go in and out before this great People; and moreover give you Victory, and Peace, and Length of Days; and at laſt may Angels convey Your Souls into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom. This is the conſtant prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties Moſt Humble, moſt Loyal, and moſt Devoted Subject and Servant,</hi> Tim. Wilſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95438:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Apoſtle aſſerts in the 13th Chap. of the Epiſtle to the</hi> Romans, That all Emperors, Kings, Princes and Governors, receive their Power from God. And that the Right of the Sword is delivered to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate by God. And therefore all are obliged to be ſubject to the Higher Powers, and not to reſiſt. And whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and ſhall receive damnation.</head>
            <p>FOR the right underſtanding whereof, I ſhall premiſe theſe Principles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All Dominion is Gods.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God gives Dominion and Power to ſome perſons over others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Law of Nature (which is the Divine Law unwritten) is a Rule, by which all Nations ſhould walk.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Law of Nature teacheth all Inferiours to honour their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours; and Subjects to pay Tribute, honorary Gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to their Kings.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſame Law of Nature ſecures every mans Propriety; ſo that there can be no Alienation, without conſent, explicite, or implicite. There is (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle, Rhet. b.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13.) as all divine, by Nature a common juſt and unjuſt, though there be no mutual communication, nor compact.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The holy Scriptures do not contradict the Law of Nature; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form mankind more plainly what is duty.</p>
            <p>Laſtly; The ſacred Hiſtorian <hi>Moſes,</hi> and other holy Writers leave Poſitive and Political Laws to be practiſed according to the Uſage of ſeveral Countries.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe (as the known truth is) that God Created <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve:</hi> And <hi>Adam</hi> begat <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi> Now what Land, or what ſubſtance and goods <hi>Adam</hi> gave <hi>Abel,</hi> he had Right to by the Law of Nature, as well as what he got by his own induſtry and labour. Neither could <hi>Adam</hi> or <hi>Cain</hi> take any of <hi>Abels</hi> Flock without ſinning againſt God, tho' there had been no Agreement between them. For this Law was written in <hi>Adams</hi> heart, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet any thing that is thy Neighbours.</hi> There is a Natural Right, and there is a Civil Right: Natural Right is by the Law of Nature. <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> were before there was any written Law. Civil Right is that which the Municipal Laws of every Countrey gives. And (if good, and conſonant to Reaſon) they are but confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or explications of the Law of Nature, or concluſions drawn from it, or ſecurities of mens Lives, Goods and Poſſeſſions, from wicked men, who would uſe no conſcience. <hi>We know</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10.) <hi>that the Law is good, if a man uſe it lawfully; knowing this, that the Law is not made for a righteous man, but for the lawleſs and diſobedient,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95438:4"/>
            <p>Government as Government agreeth to Heathens, Jews, Turks and Chriſtians, all alike. It is man as man who is the object thereof. The Nature, and Definition, and Properties are the ſame. The holy Scriptures intend not to teach us to be Politicians, no more than to be Philoſophers; but to be Chriſtians, and make us wiſe to ſalvation. The Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Right Reaſon, is the Rule of Political Government. And all Civil, or Municipal Laws, are to be ſquared by it, and ſo directed to the publick good, as their end.</p>
            <p>But more particularly, for the illuſtration hereof,
<list>
                  <item>1. I ſhall conſider what Government is.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſeveral kinds thereof.</item>
                  <item>3. I ſhall ſhew the Latitude of Subjection.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall conſider what Government is. Government is Power or Authority, which ſome men have over others, derived from God, and exerciſed according to Agreement, for the good of the whole Society.</p>
            <p>In this Deſcription, </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. We have the general Nature, Power or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</item>
               <item>2. The Author of Government; it is derived from God.</item>
               <item>3. The formal Reaſon; it is exerciſed according to Agreement.</item>
               <item>4. The End; for the good of the whole Society.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. We have the general Nature, Power or Authority. Government generally conſidered, denotes ſuperiority of Office and Authority. Where there is no Authority, there can be no Government, nor no Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or Subjection due. Power or Authority (ſaith <hi>Camero</hi>) is that whereby a perſon may claim any thing to himſelf without the injury of any other. Thus a Father exerciſes his Power, when he commands his Children: A Maſter over his Servants: And a King over his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have the Author of Government. It is derived from God. There is no Power but of God. All Dominion is Gods. <hi>The Kingdom is the Lords,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>and he is the Governour among the Nations. And the Lord hath prepared his Throne in the Heavens, and his Kingdom ruleth over all,</hi> Pſal. 22.28. <hi>and</hi> 103.19. <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes decree juſtice. By me Princes rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the Earth,</hi> Prov. 8.15, 16. God is the Abſolute Monarch over all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Formal Reaſon, It is exerciſed according to Agreement. My Opinion is this; Government in general is of the Law of Nature; but in ſpecial, whether Monarchical Abſolute, or Limited and Conditional; whether by Hereditary Succeſſion, or by Election, is according to Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Humane Law and Compact. So that the People, or Fathers of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies were at liberty to chuſe, what Form of Government they thought moſt convenient, and Fundamentally to fix the Conſtitution. Which may not be altered but by the ſame means or power. Thus Power in general is of God, as <hi>Solomon,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay. But the Specification,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95438:4"/>Limitation, and firſt Deſignation of the Perſon, or Form is by Humane Right, or Poſitive Law, according to the Diſcretion of the Aſſembly of the People. And this ſeems to me evident by Scripture and Reaſon. Thus the Higher Powers are the Ordinance of God, ſaith St. <hi>Paul.</hi> And the Emperor is the Ordinance of Man, ſaith St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Mankind is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſubject to none but God, or whom God ſhall appoint. But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> are left at Liberty to chuſe what Perſon or Form of Government any free Multitude can agree upon. This Opinion ſeems conſonant to the Doctrine and Hiſtory of the Holy Scriptures; the conſtant Practice of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or rather the People of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, is conſonant to the Principles of the Law of Nature; and is neither Erroneous in Divinity, nor dangerous in Policy. And expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſheweth that the beſt and moſt conſcientious Subjects pay Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, according to the ſeveral Laws and Cuſtoms of their Countreys. The Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> was written either in the Reign of <hi>Claudius Caeſar,</hi> or of <hi>Nero.</hi> As for <hi>Claudius,</hi> Hiſtorians tell us that he hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the Souldiers proclaimed him Emperor, and both the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and the Senate agreed to his Election. And as for <hi>Nero,</hi> his <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quennium,</hi> or firſt five years were admired by all, and had the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beſt Men, while he followed the Advice of <hi>Seneca,</hi> and other grave Counſellors. And tho' afterwards he proved a cruel Tyrant and Perſecutor, yet the Laws and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire in Civil things were good and juſt. And in thoſe things of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, even <hi>Nero</hi>'s commands were to be obeyed Actively: As is plain, <hi>For there is no Power but of God, and Rulers are not a terror to good Works, but to the evil, and he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</hi> And therefore pay <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, Tribute, Cuſtom, Fear, Honour, or whatever the Laws of your Countrey and Conſcience, and the Laws of God require of you, without Reſiſtance: <hi>For they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And this is the Judgment of all the Famous School-men, either Ancient or Modern, whom I have either read, or look'd into. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I ſtand amazed that this Doctrine ſhould have no more Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers in <hi>England,</hi> when in all other Diſputes our Engliſh Divines are the moſt rational Men in the World. But to uſe St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother caſe, <hi>I bear them record that they have a Zeal for Monarchy, but not according to Knowledge.</hi> Yet let them know, that as far as I can find by ſearch, it is the united Determination of all Politicians, School-men, and Divines, who purpoſely handle the Controverſies, that tho' Prince and Subject are Relatives, yet (<hi>prioritate rationis,</hi> or <hi>Ordine naturae intendentis,</hi> as Logicians ſpeak) in nature and time Subjects were firſt inſtituted, and Princes were conſtituted for the Subjects ſake on certain conditions, unleſs you follow the example of ſuch as deſign'd Tyranny. From whence it follows, that Subjects were no Born for Kings, but Kings or Princes, and Governours ought to promote the profit of Subjects. I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95438:5"/>have as much reaſon as any of your Majeſties Subjects to value your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Crown, Dignity, Honour, and Proſperity, and the Succeſſion to your Heirs, yet I follow the old Maxim, <hi>Malim veris offendere quàm pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere adulando.</hi> I think nothing becomes a Prieſt ſo much as Integrity. I am ſure that no Man can deny, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Higher Powers commanding things lawful, or of the Civil Legal commands of the Higher Powers; and theſe muſt not be reſiſted. But they miſtake, who think that this command of the Apoſtles was given to Chriſtians to be obedient to <hi>Nero</hi> in his unlawful commands. Whereas the Apoſtles command in this place (ſaith a Learned Divine) reacheth to all times, and is made to all that are Chriſtians: Tho' they did live under <hi>Nero,</hi> yet it doth not follow, that the Apoſtle commands them to be ſubject to him in Unlawfuls. If indeed <hi>Nero</hi>'s commands were only unlawful, and this Direction of the Apoſtle was made only to Chriſtians in thoſe times, and that ſubjection commanded were only ſuffering ſubjection, then this Scripture might make much more for Non-reſiſtance. But tho' <hi>Nero</hi> was an Enemy to the Chriſtians, yet ſome of his commands were lawful; and this Direction of the Apoſtle was not made only to Chriſtians in thoſe times, but as a general rule for all good Men. And the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Subjection here commanded, was not only to be Paſſive, but Active. This Scripture commands Active Obedience to the Higher Powers in all things which concern the Duty of Subjects, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good.</p>
            <p>And as for the Inſtances in Scripture out of the Books of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles,</hi> it is plain that there was a Covenant between the King and People. And after the Depoſing of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> all the Congregation made a Covenant with the King in the Houſe of God, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 23.3. And what doth a Covenant ſignifie, if it may not be defended and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? If ſuch a dead Dog as I am, were worthy to admoniſh an Engliſh Monarch, I would adviſe him to make Law the Rule of his Reign, and ſhew his Prerogative in Acts of Bounty, Mercy, and Mitigation of the Rigour of ſome ſevere Laws: And I would not tell him, that it is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion for an Innocent Subject to defend himſelf. And yet I imagine that I am as great a Friend to Monarchy, and to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the greateſt Paſſive-Obedience-Doctor is.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We have the End of Government, For the good of the whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diety. Power and Authority is ordained of God for the Happineſs of Mankind. By this we are legally ſecured againſt wicked Men in our Houſes, Poſſeſſions, Lands, and Eſtates; in our Liberties, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and in whatſoever belongs to us as Members of a Civil Society. Political Order is a juſt Diſpoſition between King and Subject, as well as between Subject and Subject. God is the Author and Lover of Order; and an Enemy of Diſorder and Confuſion. And Government was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the ſingular Wiſdom and Providence of God for the good of his Creatures.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95438:5"/>
            <p>From hence I may deduce theſe Inferences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence the Power and Authority of Kings and Governours is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Divine. They are conſtituted Rulers by God, and are his Miniſters. And therefore Honour and Obedience is due to them for the Lords ſake, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence it follows evidently, That Princes and Governours ought to Rule in Gods fear, and ſo perform their Office as Gods Vicegerents, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring Juſtice impartially, knowing whoſe Authority they have. Hence Princes are called Paſtors of the People, and Fathers of the Countrey. And ſhould bear the Name of Gods, and Children of the moſt High, not only in Power, but in Goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence it neceſſarily follows that all Subjects ought to reverence and honour their King and Governours with moſt humble Service, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and Obedience in all things. But of this more anon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall conſider the ſeveral kinds. The moſt common Diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is into Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, and Democracy.</p>
            <p>The firſt kind or Form of Government is Monarchy. I approve of this as beſt, according to the ſaying of the moſt Famous Poet, <hi>The Rule of many is not good.</hi> Let there be one Ruler, one King, to whom God gives the Scepter. He is King, who hath Supream Power, ſubject to none.</p>
            <p>And a Monarch is either Abſolute, or Conditional. And again, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Elective, or Succeſſive. Elective, when in a Kingdom a Perſon of a new Family, or of the ſame Family is choſen. Succeſſive, when the next Heir, Male, and in ſome Kingdoms the Female, is owned and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. Thus the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> is by Inheritance and Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And our King never dies, as we ſay. But the King of <hi>England</hi> is not Abſolute, but Limited: And hath Lords, and Commons, without whom he cannot make, nor repeal Laws. And we have <hi>Magna Charta</hi> unviolable: And the Subjects great Felicity, and no leſs the Kings Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, who Rules not over Slaves, but Freemen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall ſhew the Latitude of Subjection. It is a Civil Filial Fear of the King: And excludes all things that tend to his Diſhonour, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all things that tend to his Honour. It contains all Duties and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices required of Subjects to their Prince. There is an univerſal Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (next under, and after God) in all things Legal due to the King, who Reigns by the Ordinance and Appointment of God. Native Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and true Chriſtianity is the greateſt Intereſt of Princes. A good Conſcience and pious Heart abhors Obmurmurations, Factions, Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Rebellions, or whatſoever can be conceived to diſturb the Souls ſubjection to the Higher Powers. It is groſs Hypocriſie to pretend to follow the Holy Jeſus, and not render to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which are <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>'s. I am ſure that Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught Subjection to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, as the Ornament and Honour of their Religion.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95438:6"/>
            <p>This Subjection, firſt, forbids light and vain thoughts of the Kings Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uttering Wicked and Trayterous words; ſpeaking evil of him. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy People,</hi> Exod. 22.28. <hi>And curſe not the King, no not in thy Thought,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.20. And the Holy Ghoſt brands them with the odious name of <hi>filthy Dreamers, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> St. <hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 8. In brief, It excludes all retaining of his Dues, Tribute, Cuſtom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all Cheating him of his Revenue; all Diſobedience to his wholſom Laws; all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt or Violation offered to his Sacred Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Subjection includes or comprehends all Duties of a Chriſtian Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to his King. For that which is in one place, Let every Soul be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Higher Powers, is in another, Fear the King, and Honour the King. And in the Fifth Commandment, Honour thy Father and Mother. Here as by Father and Mother all Superiors are meant; (not only our Natural Parents, but alſo our Political Father, our Governours, eſpecially the Supream Magiſtrate, the King: As it is well explained in our Church-Catechiſm, To Honour and Obey the King, and all that are put in Authority under him: Which alſo is the Interpretation of all ſober Divines.) So by this word Honour, all kinds of Duty and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices from all Inſeriors to their Superiors reſpectively, are compriſed. So to Honour, as to Fear, Love and Obey them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is expreſſed alſo by St. <hi>Peter, Submit your ſelves unto every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well,</hi> This is yet more fully and largely ſet down by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 13. Where this Doctrine is not only declared, but preſſed and confirmed by many ſtrong and ſolid Reaſons. We muſt needs be ſubject not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake, <hi>v.</hi> 5. If you make Conſcience of your ways, give the King his Due. There is nothing more plain than this Chapter for Subjection to the King, and Submiſſion and reſpect to his Officers without murmuring and repining, when according to Law they demand their Dues. The humble Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and obedient Subject, who willingly ſubmits to the Kings Laws, may be aſſured that in that particular he pleaſeth God, and he always hath the Teſtimony and Satisfaction of a good Conſcience. But the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and diſobedient, who will not render to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, aſſuredly diſpleaſeth God, and can never quiet his Conſcience; but runs the hazard of a moſt ignominious eſteem in the World, and of Eternal Damnation in the World to come.</p>
            <p>And verily Reſiſting Governours is not leſs unbecoming the Reaſon of a man, than the Patience and Humility of a Chriſtian: For the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer is armed with Authority, but the contumacious Oppoſer hath nothing to defend or plead for him, but Arbitrary Power, wilful Perverſeneſs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95438:6"/>and ſtubborn Humour, which in cold blood or ſober conſideration muſt be acknowledged far more dangerous than the evil the Reſiſtant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to remedy.</p>
            <p>And here if ye demand the manner of this Subjection: I anſwer, True Chriſtian Subjects bear to the King, ſuch a Submiſſion as Children to their Parents: Not a terrifying and amazing, but a reſpectful and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential Subjection. The King is the Father of his Countrey, and all his Loving and Loyal Subjects are as ſo many Children to him.</p>
            <p>This Subjection alſo doth imply, 1. A real and eminent Love of the King. Gods own People <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid of King <hi>David, Thou art worth ten thouſand of us,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. Hence the King is called <hi>The breath of our noſtrils, Lam.</hi> 4.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Subjection doth imply Fidelity and adhering to the King at all times, and in all conditions. The King, and his Subjects, are united in their Political capacity, as the Head and the Body: Their welfare is conjoyned, and cannot be ſeparated. And this Fidelity is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, when it comes from a touch of Gods finger; from the Grace of his holy Spirit. As we read there went with <hi>Saul</hi> a band of men, whoſe hearts God had touched, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.26. But ſuch as clave not to him are ſtigmatized for Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> who deſpiſed their King, <hi>v.</hi> 27. For Fidelity alſo we have the example of <hi>Davids</hi> Servants; <hi>Behold thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are ready to do whatſoever my Lord the King ſhall appoint,</hi> 2 Sam. 15. v. 15. <hi>And</hi> Ittai (that Loyal heart; that noble and conſtant ſpirit) <hi>ſaid to the King</hi> (when <hi>David</hi> went to perſwade him to go back, and to take care of his own ſafety) <hi>As the Lord liveth, and as my Lord the King liveth, ſurely in what place my Lord the King ſhall be, whether in death or life, even there alſo will thy Servant be; v.</hi> 21. Here was a faithful Servant and Loyal Subject indeed; and herein he evidenced himſelf no leſs obedient to the Law of God, by which we are bound in Conſcience to help the King againſt his Enemies. And thus to adhere to the King (by being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Truſt repoſed in us; in being juſt in our places, and ready to help in all difficulties) is a right and ſure way to make a Kingdom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible and terrible to Enemies. Diviſions, Conſpiracies, and Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations in a State, expoſe it to forreign Enemies. <hi>A Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> ſaith the wiſe Counſellor, the Son of God. But Unity of heart and affections between Subjects and their Sovereign, renders a Kingdom proſperous at home, and formidable abroad.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Prayer to God for him. Our Religion, the Law of our God, our Chriſtianity as well as our Fidelity, Loyalty and Affection, call for this at our hands. The bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to this duty, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I think that the Collects of our Church for the King and Queen, are both wiſe and Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thankſgiving to God for any mercy to the King. <hi>I exhort that Thankſgivings be made,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. The Infinite Majeſty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95438:7"/>is the Ocean, from which flow all bleſſings that we mortals receive. It is he that giveth great Deliverance to his King, and ſheweth mercy to his Anointed, to <hi>David,</hi> and to his ſeed for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.49, 50. Therefore ſhould we give thanks unto the Lord, and ſing praiſes to his holy Name. Eſpecially let us praiſe God for the wonderful and happy Deliverance of this Church and Nation by our <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who hath by the Divine favour and bleſſing ſaved us, and put a ſtop to the Malice and Cruelty of all the Churches Enemies. <hi>This is the Lords doing, and it is marvelous in our eyes.</hi> And as great a mercy as ever this Nation and Church enjoyed: Tho' through an unnatural Principle the Prejudices of many wiſe and pious men have made them ungrateful to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, who are in truth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Benefactors, not only to all Engliſh Proteſtants, but to all the Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>And that theſe Prejudices may be removed, and that all your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may give God, and your Majeſties thanks, hath been my conſtant deſire and labour. And tho' I know that the multitude are prone to Innovations and Changes, and too apt to be ſeduced, yet in this Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution they are to be juſtified, ſo far as they defended their Religion, Laws and Liberties. And I challenge any learned and conſcientious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine to diſpute the Caſe in Print before God and the World.</p>
            <p>And therefore I humbly beg your Sacred Majeſties pardon, while I make Animadverſions on the Reverend Dr. <hi>William Sherlocks</hi> Book, intituled, <hi>The Caſe of Allegiance due to Sovereign Powers, ſtated and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, according to Scripture and Reaſon, and the Principles of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>I cannot believe that falſe Principles in Government conduce to your Majeſties ſervice. And for this reaſon among others I think it my duty to oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>I do believe that the Reverend Dr. acts according to the preſent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of his Conſcience, (as he ſpeaks in the beginning of his Preface) and I do not take him either for a diſhoneſt man, or a fool. But, as he ſaith, he may be miſtaken, and ſo may any body elſe, tho' never ſo wiſe and honeſt. And he ſaith ingenuouſly, that if any man can ſhew him, that the Principles he acts on are falſe, uncertain, or precarious, and ſuch as cannot reaſonably ſatisfie an honeſt and unbiaſſed mind, he will confeſs that his deſire of ſatisfaction ſecretly and inſenſibly diſtorted his Judgment, tho he took all poſſible care that it ſhould not. I do, as I would be done by, and I believe that many have refuſed the Oaths upon Principles of Conſcience, tho' I believe their Conſciences erroneous. And I hope to make it evident, if, as the Dr's phraſe is, they will deliver themſelves from the Tyranny of Prepoſſeſſion and Prejudice, § 2. p. 10.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Animadverſion on Section 1.</head>
               <p>The Dr. ſaith, <hi>That which hath perplexed this Controverſie, is the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixing the Diſpute of Right with the Duty of Obedience, or making the Legal
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95438:7"/>Right of Princes to their Thrones the only Reaſon and Foundation of the Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance of Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I cannot imagine that any Obedience is due, but to him only who hath Right. If he hath no Right, why ſhould I pay him Obedience? The Scripture ſaith, <hi>Fear to whom fear, honour to whom honour.</hi> I muſt know therefore to whom it is due. The Scripture ſuppoſeth all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to know ſome other way, to whom Obedience, Fear and Honour is due. For I take it for granted, and as that which all Learned men will own, that the Scripture is not a Rule of Policy, or Political Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, any more than it is of Logick, Aſtronomy, or any part of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy; which are Arts and Sciences of themſelves. And ſo Policy hath Rules and Methods of its own, and depends upon the Senſe and Reaſon of all Mankind, being not proper to Chriſtians, but common to Jews, Turks or Heathens. And beſides, the Engliſh Policy is not the ſame with other Chriſtian Nations.</p>
               <p>Now as to our preſent Government and Revolution, Engliſh-men may be divided into theſe three Ranks.</p>
               <p>Firſt; Such as joyned with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> before or at his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to his Declaration, Expectation, Deſire, and Invitation of them.</p>
               <p>Secondly; Such as did not joyn with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> but did op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him, either with their Prayers, or with their Strength, or with both; but ſince have taken the Oaths of Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly; Such as did neither joyn with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> nor ſince have taken the Oaths.</p>
               <p>The Reverend Dr. is among the Moderate men of the ſecond Rank: (And <hi>est quiddam prodire tenus:</hi> It is ſomething to come thus far; we have the ſhorter way to our Journeys end, as one ſaith.) For he writes thus, <hi>Many things are ſaid (for the justifying the Legality of the late Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution) which may make men much more moderate in the point than ſome are,</hi> § 1. <hi>p.</hi> 2. And his endeavour is to perſwade thoſe of the third Rank to take the Oaths; (a very honeſt, charitable and pious endeavour) for he ſaith well in his Preface, <hi>There are others who are ſtill diſſatisfied about the Oaths, and are deſirous to try, whether they can find that ſatisfaction, which he hath done.</hi> This, I confeſs, is a good Reaſon, which may in charity oblige me.</p>
               <p>To proceed; All Learned men know what it is to ſuppoſe or put a Caſe, and I will not be a quarrelſom Antagoniſt; but will be as civil to the Dr. as he can be to me; and therefore for his ſuppoſition, I will not charge him with reflecting upon this preſent Government; which he ſaith, and I believe he ſpeaks his conſcience and heart, <hi>he is very ſure, he is far from intending to do, in the latter end of his Preface.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Dr. ſeems to make a contradiſtinction between Right, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95438:8"/>in theſe words, § 1. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>Allegiance is due only to Right, not to Government, tho' it can be paid only to Government.</hi> Now I think there can be no Government, where there is no Right: For who ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and who ſhould obey, where there is no Right to command? Otherwiſe how could there be ſuch a thing as Anarchy, or Confuſion, when every man doth what is good in his own Eyes, as when there was no King or Governour in <hi>Iſrael? Judg.</hi> 19.1.</p>
               <p>And again <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>If then Allegiance be due, not for the ſake of Legal Right, but Government.</hi> But I ſay there is no Allegiance due, where there is no Legal Right: (either Natural or Poſitive;) for I ſuppoſe all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory Laws founded upon Natural Principles. Again, the Dr. aſſerts, <hi>That God placeth and ſetteth ſome Princes on the Throne, tho' they have no Legal or Humane Right, p.</hi> 3. Now this ſeems to me a Riddle. I am of Opinion, that every Prince, who hath Gods Authority, hath a Legal and Humane Right; unleſs God immediately from Heaven by an Angel, or the like extraordinary way, gives him Authority. But no Prince or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily hath Gods Authority but by Legal and Humane Right; as will appear hereafter.</p>
               <p>As for what the Dr. ſaith about the Diſpoſal of Providence, it ſeems to me pure Enthuſiaſm, and the very Dregs of Quakeriſm; which I ſhall conſider in due place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Animadverſions on § 2.</head>
               <p>As for what the Dr. ſaith in this Section, and quotes out of Biſhop <hi>Overals</hi> Convocation-Book, I admit and approve <hi>ſano ſenſu,</hi> and I reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence their Authority: And I ſuppoſe that at that time there were ſome Divines, perhaps Biſhops, in that Convocation, who did think Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Arms lawful in ſome caſes, and founded Government in Agreement; as the ever-renowned Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> and Dr. <hi>Bilſon</hi> certainly did. And when the Dr. proves the contrary, I will believe him, and before, I ſuppoſe, he doth not deſire that I ſhould.</p>
               <p>But let us ſee the Dr's. Inferences from the Doctrine of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Men may diſpute any thing, but I know not how it was poſſible for the Convocation to expreſs their ſenſe plainer; <hi>That all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Powers, when throughly ſetled, have Gods Authority, and must be obeyed.</hi> So that here are two great Points determined, whereupon this whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie turns.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That thoſe Princes, who have no Legal Right to their Thrones, may yet have Gods Authority. But ſurely the Convocation meant, that they had a Legal Right, and were no longer Uſurpers, when they had Gods Authority; as the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and King <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the Emperors of <hi>Rome.</hi> Let him prove the contrary if he can. And I am fully of this Opinion, which, I think, is the Dr's That there is <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum quod ſic,</hi> as the Schools call it, a Time, when all Uſurpers, or Invading Powers have Gods Authority, and muſt be obeyed; and that is when they are throughly ſetled.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95438:8"/>
               <p>But the Queſtion is, <hi>When they are throughly ſetled?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is hard to determine and fix a time; but there is a time when Invaders and Conquerors have a Right and Title to the Crown. And I am of Opinion this is, When ſuch a Prince and People have made a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Compact or Agreement, explicite or implicite: When having with a good Conſcience defended their King, Laws, and Countrey, as long as they could, they yield, being taken Priſoners, or ſubdued. And let this conſent be ſuppoſed to be over-awed, yet conſent it is; eſpecially when they have made a Solemn Promiſe or Oath to ſuch a Prince. And he that breaks ſuch a Promiſe or Oath is wicked. <hi>David</hi> deſcribes a Citizen of <hi>Zion</hi> thus, <hi>He that ſweareth to his own hurt, and changeth not, Pſal.</hi> 15.4. This is grounded upon this Natural Principle, That what Promiſe I make, if lawful, however inconvenient to me, I muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
               <p>By the way, I call an Explicite Covenant, when there is the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Conſent and Profeſſion of ſuch an Ingagement made by a National Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>I call an Implicite Covenant, when the Members of a Society in their Practice do all ſuch Acts, as are required by the Rules agreed among them, and ſubmit themſelves thereunto: Tho' they make no verbal Promiſe or Profeſſion thereof. I need not illuſtrate this in our Caſe; for all Men have ſeen with their Eyes, and heard with their Ears what hath been done among us.</p>
               <p>Or, in the Drs words, § 2. p. 9. <hi>The Government is throughly ſettled, when the whole Adminiſtration of the Government, and the whole Power of the Nation is in the Hands of the Prince, when every thing is done in his Name, and by his Authority, when the Eſtates of the Realm, and the great Body of the Nation have ſubmitted to him, and thoſe who will not ſubmit, can be cruſhed by him, whenever he pleaſeth:</hi> If this be not a ſettled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I deſpair of ever knowing what it is.</p>
               <p>Now I ſay, in plain Engliſh, This is a mutual Covenant between Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and Governed, and gives the Formality of Relation between King and Subject. But then in this Caſe the King hath an Humane and Legal Right, as well as Gods Authority; which the Dr. ſeems every where to deny. For he infers, pag 5. <hi>Therefore thoſe Princes, who have no Legal Right, may have Gods Authority.</hi> But I ſay, That tho' ſuch Princes, as the Convocation ſpeaks of, had no Legal Right before, yet when they are throughly ſettled, they have Legal Right. And this is the difference between the Dr. and me. And, pag. 9. The Submiſſion of a Prince indeed may be thought neceſſary to transfer a Legal Right; but the Submiſſion of the People, it ſelf, is ſufficient to ſettle the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and when it is ſettled, then it is the Authority of God, whatever the Humane Right be. See pag. 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He ſeems to aſſert, That no Right can be Legal and Humane, but Succeſſive or Hereditary Right, § 4. p. 26.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95438:9"/>
               <p>I know Great, Learned, and Pious Authors, who are of this Opinion, as I have propoſed it; and the Dr. cannot appear ſingular in it, and to advance Paradoxes, as he ſpeaks, § 1. p. 3. to any Man who hath throughly ſtudied theſe Controverſies. But then all, or moſt of thoſe Divines, and Politicians aſſert Defenſive Arms in ſome Caſe: And that the ſeveral Forms of Regiment are according to Agreement, or an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Man: And they uſually ſay, that the Call of the People is Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to Magiſtracy in ſuch extraordinary Caſe: And ſo the Powers that are, are ordained of God, and muſt not be reſiſted.</p>
               <p>Again, if the Dr. means, firſt, By Actual Poſſeſſion of the Throne, the Power of the Sword, or Strength, or the Princes being in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and having the Royal Forts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at his Command, then this alone can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give Right, tho' it is the Diſpoſal of Providence. And this I take to be Hobbiſm, Scepticiſm, or Atheiſm. And ſuch things I have read in ſome Oliverian Pamphlets to juſtifie that Damnable Rebellion, as the Diſpoſal of Providence. And thus to ſay that Conqueſt, Election, and Uſurpation were all one to the Primitive Chriſtians, as ſome of late have ſaid, is moſt abominable, and to be exploded. And the Reverend Dr. verges ſo near this, that I wiſh he would explain himſelf better, if it be not his meaning. See § 4. p. 18. <q rend="inline">The Scripture hath given us no Direction in this Caſe, but to Submit and pay all Obedience of Subjects to the preſent Powers. It makes no Diſtinction, that ever I could find between a Rightful King and an Uſurper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Scriptures, not being an abſolute Rule of Policy, as I ſaid before, ſuppoſe that we know, who is our King or Governour, or who are the Higher Powers, by Reaſon, and the ſeveral Laws and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Immemorial Uſages of ſeveral Countries. And then inſtruct Subjects in their Duty. But of this Section I ſhall ſpeak in its Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the Dr. means by Actual Poſſeſſion of the Throne, ſuch a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or Settlement, as is before mentioned, then I ſay, whoever hath ſuch a Settlement, hath not only Gods Authority, but Humane and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right; tho' he is not the next Heir, or immediate Lineal Succeſſor. And of ſuch a Prince <hi>I</hi> grant, the Subjects need not inquire, <hi>Quo jure, quâve injuriâ,</hi> as the Schools ſpeak, he came to the Throne: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had Reaſon to Invade, or Conquer, or not. He is King, and hath Gods Authority, and muſt be obeyed. And in this caſe the old Maxim proves true, <hi>Vox Populi eſt Vox Dei,</hi> The voice of the People is the voice of God. God chuſeth whom the People in this manner chuſe. But I do not think that any rational Politician, or judicious Divine grounds this Poſition upon the Diſpoſal of Providence firſtly: I am ſure, moſt do not.</p>
               <p>But upon ſuch Principles as theſe;</p>
               <p n="1">1. No one Form of Government is Natural or Moral, but purely of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95438:9"/>Poſitive Agreement. And tho' it is good Manners in the Subjects of a Monarch, eſpecially of an Engliſh Monarch, to believe Regal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beſt; and to believe that Hereditary Government, or Monarchy, is moſt prudential and excellent: And that Lineal Succeſſion is not to be altered but upon very ſufficient grounds. And tho' no Man ought to meddle with them that are given to change; (which may poſſibly befall a King, as well as his Subjects) yet no Man can with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence condemn any other lawful Form of Government. As the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Conſuls, and Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> of old: Or the Government of the Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> or Senate at preſent: Or the States General of the United Provinces. All whoſe Subjects are to obey, and not reſiſt their ſeveral Sovereigns, by St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s command, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. For they have their Power of God, and Gods Authority.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Publick Good is the Sovereign Law of all. And ſo tho' Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have Sworn to maintain their Sovereign, yet if he, and they are Conquered, and the Conqueror gives them their Lives, Liberties, or Eſtates, whereupon they Promiſe or Swear Allegiance to him, they muſt for the future own him as their Soveraign Lord. Or, if they are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly oppreſſed, ſo that the Publick Good of their Countrey or the Preſervation of their Laws, Liberties, and Religion requires them to forſake their King, who (as I ſuppoſe) would have brought them into Slavery; or Non-aſſiſtance, as the Dr. confeſſeth, when a loving, vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and good Friend comes to ſave their Religion, Laws, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. In this caſe the Subjects ought to obey him that hath Actual Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Throne. For he is their Elected King, and hath Humane, Legal, and Divine Right.</p>
               <p>And this ſecures Princes from Factious, Seditious, and Rebellious Subjects. And ſecures Subjects from Wicked, Cruel, and Ill-deſigning, or Ill-adviſed Princes, who follow evil Counſellors, to the Subverſion of the Laws, and Ruine of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>And this I think may be proved from the Drs. own Aſſertions, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in this Book.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He aſſerts, p. 14. <hi>Sometimes God not only places a ſingle Perſon in the Throne, but intails it on his Family by Humane Laws, and makes the Throne a Legal Inheritance.</hi> And p. 24. <hi>Hereditary Right is either a continued <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, which can give no Right, or a Right by Law, that is by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People to intail the Crown on ſuch a Family.</hi> Now all Laws are made by the Advice and Conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons. From whence it follows that the Dr. muſt own, that Hereditary Monarchy is ſo made by the People; and that ſuch a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch receives all his Power (for he hath no Power, but Legal) from them as well as from God. And as for what follows, <hi>which,</hi> ſaith the Dr. I obſerved before, <hi>If Right be reſolved into the Choice and Conſent of the People, cannot be done; for what Right had my Anceſtors three or four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ago, to chuſe a King for me?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95438:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I am afraid the Dr. next time will ſay, That the Laws of former Parliaments, made ſome years ago, do not bind us, tho' not repealed. And none but preſent Parliaments can make Laws for us. We have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with our Forefathers; we muſt perſonally conſent to all Laws. Phy! for ſhame Dr. let us hear no more of this. For I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident you do not believe, that our Anceſtors had no Right to make Laws for us, or to chuſe a King for us. A King is a King to Children Born of Parents, who have choſen him, or his Family, and ſuch Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are his Subjects without a perſonal and verbal Ingagement: And former Laws bind us without a new Act of Parliament to confirm them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Dr. aſſerts, p. 36. <hi>If they</hi> (that is, Sovereign Princes) <hi>receive their Authority from Men,</hi> (which they do, as well as from God, ſay we) <hi>and Humane Laws,</hi> (which the Dr. confeſſed before) <hi>I cannot imagine that their Power is any more than a Truſt, of which they muſt give an account to thoſe who have intruſted them with it, according to thoſe Laws, by which they were intruſted to exerciſe that Power. For whether there be any expreſs Proviſion made in the Law to call them to an Account or no, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing proves, that if they receive their Power from Men, they are accountable to them. For thoſe who give Power may take an Account of the uſe and abuſe of it.</hi> This, with the Drs. Conceſſions hereafter mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, proves the Lawfulneſs, Reaſonableneſs, and Conſcience of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Revolution. And, p. 25. he ſaith, <hi>A Legal Intail is nothing more than the Authority of the People.</hi> So that the Authority of the People (I mean, either the Convention of Eſtates, which is an extraordinary Aſſembly, or the Parliament, which is the ordinary Aſſembly) gives Humane and Legal Right. And ſuch a Prince is ſet upon the Throne by God, and is by the Diſpoſal of Providence, and is Gods Miniſter for the good of the People. So that what the Dr. ſaith in the beginning of p. 25. is very weak, To ſay <hi>that God ſets up no Prince, who aſcends the Throne without Humane Right and Legal,</hi> is to ſay, that ſome Kings are removed, and others ſet up, but not by God; which is directly contradictory to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; It is to ſay, That the Four Monarchies were not ſet up by God, becauſe they all began by Violence and Uſurpation; It is ſay, That God, as well as Men, is confined by Humane Laws, in making Kings; It is to ſay, That the Right of Government is not derived from God, without the Conſent of the People. For if God cannot make Kings without the People, or againſt their Conſent declared by their Laws, the Authority muſt be derived from the People, not from God; or at leaſt, if it be Gods Authority, yet God cannot give it himſelf without the People, nor otherwiſe than as they have directed him by their Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If we ſpeak of Gods Abſolute Power, he can ſend a Legion of Angels, and ſet the Crown upon a Kings Head, or by any like extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95438:10"/>Nomination and Means. But we ſay (and I hope the Dr. upon conſideration will not deny it) that Right Reaſon, Natural Conſcience, Law, and Scripture are the Rule of our Duty; and by theſe means God cooperates, and his Divine Providence concurs with men. And when the Dr. is in his ſenſes, and argues like himſelf, that is, a Divine of his Reputation and Station in the Church, he will tell you, <hi>p.</hi> 65. <hi>That the King hath no Right but by Law, and then the Law may determine how far his Right ſhall extend,</hi> &amp;c. But this Revolution hath confounded the wiſdom of the wiſe, and brought to nothing the underſtanding of the prudent; inſomuch that a man may propound St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Queſtion to theſe great Doctors of our Church; <hi>Where is the Wiſe? Where is the Scribe? Where is the Diſputer of this World?</hi> Hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of this World? It is much eaſier to juſtifie the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution. I will here add the Judgment of <hi>Tol.</hi> collected by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Synopſis on <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. Power (that is, Principality or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, yea, even of Infidels and Idolaters) is not but of God, that is, from the Divine Ordination and Diſpoſition, that the wicked may be reſtrained, the juſt honoured, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from God as the firſt Beginning, and Cauſe, and Author, not indeed by himſelf, but mediately, by men, in whom God hath put this inſtinct to ſet over them thoſe that ſhould Rule them. And whoever reads the Lord <hi>Chan. Forteſcue,</hi> will find this true in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Animadverſions on Sect. 3.</head>
               <p>In this Section I ſhall animadvert on ſome of his Propoſitions; and then propoſe his Conceſſions, ſcattered all over his Book.</p>
               <p>As for the two firſt Propoſitions, I admit them: But I think that I may juſtly find fault with the third, which is, <hi>There are but three ways whereby God gives this Power and Authority to any perſon: Either by Nature, or by expreſs Nomination, or by the Diſpoſals of Providence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I ſay that this Diviſion is Illogical and naughty. Logicians ſay, that the parts of a Diviſion muſt be oppoſite; but theſe are not. For the Power and Authority, that is given by Nature, is the diſpoſal of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and the Power and Authority, that is given by expreſs Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the diſpoſal of Providence alſo. And I muſt confeſs, that in my ſmall Reading, I never met with any that made ſuch a ſort of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I ſhould have added, 3. By Covenant, or by the Election of the People. I fear that the Dr's. Enthuſiaſtical notion of Providence here impoſed upon his Learning.</p>
               <p>Let no man ſay, that I do not ſpeak of Divine Providence with that awful regard and reverence that I ought; for ſurely I juſtifie Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence much more clearly, than this abſtruſe and unaccountable notion.</p>
               <p>The Dr. goes on: <hi>By Nature, Parents have a Natural Superiority over their Children, and are their Lords and Governours too.</hi> This was the firſt Government in the World, and is the only Natural Authority: For in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95438:11"/>propriety of ſpeaking, there is no Natural Prince but a Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here obſerve that this deſtroys the Principles of Sir <hi>R. F</hi>'s. Book; with which ſo many young Divines in the Univerſity of late have been poſſeſſed, and about which they have been ſo very paſſionate, that they would endure no modeſt oppoſition; but invidiouſly declaimed againſt any man who did but call in queſtion this Principle, as if he could not be a Lover of Monarchy. If there is no Natural Prince but a Father, thens in propriety of ſpeaking, there can be no Natural Prince now in the World; but every Prince muſt be by Inſtitution, or Agreement, or the like. For the Relation of King and Subject are not Natural, as the Relation of Father and Child are. But yet I ſay, Monarchy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth neareſt to the Government of Gods Throne. And I approve of the words of the Reverend Dr. <hi>Fern,</hi> Monarchy (however we cannot ſay it is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> by Divine Precept, commanding all Nations, to be ſo governed, or <hi>Jure Naturae,</hi> by Nature's Law inforcing it) is plainly <hi>ductu Naturae,</hi> by Nature leading men from Paternal to Legal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>exemplo Divino,</hi> as I may ſay, by Divine example and inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We ſuppoſe (as the Sacred Hiſtorian tells us) that <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo <hi>Noah</hi> after the Flood, by Gods bleſſing begat Sons and Daughters. Theſe ſpread over the face of the Earth; ſome in <hi>Aſia;</hi> ſome in <hi>Africa;</hi> ſome in <hi>Europe, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe God indued with Reaſon, and they lived (or ſhould have lived) by the Light of Nature, Gods own Law written in their hearts. (And as face anſwereth to face in a glaſs; ſo the heart of man to man.) And when they encreaſed greatly, for orders ſake, or becauſe ſome were lawleſs, and, living without the fear of God, oppreſſed the weak, Natural Prudence, which is the Light of God in Man, taught them to Covenant with one Ruler, and to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſociety and mutual help, and ſome Rules, Laws and Cuſtoms to determine Controverſies between Family and Family; Man or Man for the publick good. To this firſt Conſtitution all were bound, both Rulers, and Ruled; and this could not be changed (ordinarily) but by the Heads of ſuch Societies, or Families. If any man can diſprove this by Reaſon, or Scripture, we would gladly ſee it.</p>
               <p>As for our own Countrey, it is manifeſt in the moſt antient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and Chronicles that ever I read, that we have been governed by Kings all along. But we have had an Heptarchy, and not always Lineal Succeſſion. And when <hi>England</hi> was one Monarchy under <hi>Egbert,</hi> in the year of Chriſt 818. or thereabouts, we ſhall find the Succeſſion altered for the publick good; as the late Author of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> upon the account of the Oaths hath largely ſhewed out of <hi>Mat. Westminſter,</hi> and <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> and others. But ſtill all this ſuppoſeth an Agreement between the King and People originally. And no doubt Monarchy, and all Government will ſtand beſt upon its own Foundation. And what men agree to, all conſcientious men will obſerve, according
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95438:11"/>to the mutual Oath of King and People. And it is ſo far from being an inconvenience, that it is the only true and juſt Title of all Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. And it is a prejudice to the King, to ſay otherwiſe: For the beſt and wiſeſt men ſubmit only upon Condition and Covenant. We know that Nature teacheth all men to prevent Ruine; and this is the Law of God.</p>
               <p>But let us come to the Dr's. great Principle, the diſpoſal of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>God governs the rest of the World, removes Kings, and ſets up Kings, only by his Providence, that is, then God ſets up a King, when by his Providence he advanceth him to the Throne (that is, I think, God ſets up a King, when he ſets up a King;</hi> a ſelf-evident Principle) <hi>and puts the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Authority into his hands: Then he removeth a King, when by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence he thruſts him from his Throne, and takes the Government out of his hands,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I can make no other ſenſe of this, but that God doth it, when he doth it. But how ſhall it appear to us, that it is Gods Providence, either to remove, or ſet up a King?</p>
               <p>The Dr. anſwereth, <hi>There are but three ways whereby God gives this Power and Authority to any perſon; either by Nature, or by expreſs Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or by the Diſpoſal of Providence, p.</hi> 11. If this be not Trifling, I know not what is. If any man ſhould ask the Dr. Who made him Maſter of the <hi>Temple?</hi> and he ſhould anſwer, God made him ſo, or it was the diſpoſal of Providence; would he not ſmile, tho' this is true? But the Queſtion asked is about the Humane Principal Efficient, ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate to God, and his Providence. But the former never comes into queſtion among Chriſtians. It is confeſſed, it was Gods Providence that exalted <hi>Joſeph</hi> and all Kings. I can hardly forbear, but I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways reverenced the Dr. and therefore will ſay no more, but Lord have mercy upon us the ſinful Sons of <hi>Adam:</hi> O the power of Prejudice!</p>
               <p>As for Gods Providence in this Revolution, I have publiſhed my thoughts in a Diſcourſe entituled, <hi>Conſcience ſatisfied, in a Cordial and Loyal Submiſſion to the preſent Government of King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary; and I muſt refer the inquiſitive Reader to that Treatiſe, <hi>p.</hi> 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here farther, that we may conſider what the Doctor ſaith, we muſt diſtinguiſh of Gods Providence: <hi>It is either,</hi> 1. <hi>Immediate and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary; Or</hi> 2. <hi>Mediate and ordinary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The immediate and extraordinary Providence of God is, when God works what he will beſides or againſt the means and order appointed by himſelf in Nature. And this is done in all Miracles, which are effected to this end, that we may know that the Omnipotent Creator and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all things, acts moſt freely by means, or without means.</p>
               <p>And this is manifeſt either, 1. In puniſhing his Enemies: Or, 2. In preſerving his Servants. Thus God immediately by a Deluge from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven drowned the Old World; confounded the Language of the Rebels
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95438:12"/>at <hi>Babel;</hi> rained Fire and Brimſtone out of Heaven upon <hi>Sodom;</hi> drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt in the Red Sea, after all thoſe former Plagues and Judgments upon him. Thus God commanded the Earth to open and ſwallow up thoſe proud and hypocritical Rebels, <hi>Corah</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. By this the Sun ſtood ſtill, and the Moon ſtayed, till the people had avenged themſelves on their Enemies, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.13. By this, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Angel of the Lord ſmote in the Camp of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> one hundred fourſcore and five thouſand, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.35. On the other ſide, God by his extraordinary Providence gave <hi>Abraham</hi> a Son in his old age; commanded the Ravens to feed his zealous Servant <hi>Elijah;</hi> multiplied the Widdows Oil; and preſerved the three Children in the Fiery Furnace, and the like. Hence the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt concludes; <hi>The Lord alone doth great wonders, Pſal.</hi> 136.4.</p>
               <p>But I ſuppoſe the Dr. doth not mean, that God makes any King or Queen thus by Miracle. He did not ſend an Angel to ſet the Crown on their Majeſties Heads on the days of their Arrival in <hi>London,</hi> or on the day of their Election by the Convention of Eſtates, or on the day of their Coronation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore there is a mediate and ordinary Providence of God: And that is, when God by Creatures or ſecond Cauſes produceth thoſe Effects, to which thoſe Creatures or Cauſes by the conſtant, accuſtomed Order of Nature are appointed and made by God. Thus by food and nouriſhment he ſuſtains us; by Phyſick and Medicines he removes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and heals the ſick; by his Word Read and Preached he declares his will to ſinners, and perſwades them to believe and obey. Thus we read, <hi>Man doth not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord, Deut.</hi> 8.3. And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was recovered by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a lump of Figs, and laying it for a Plaiſter upon a Boyl, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.21. Finally, thus our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Parable told the rich Glutton, <hi>They have</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, let them hear them, Luk.</hi> 16.29. Thus I acknowledge it is the diſpoſal of Providence, that by the Convention of Eſtates, as Means or Inſtruments, the Prince and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Orange</hi> ſhould be King and Queen of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Dr. ſaith well, § 3. <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>Providence is Gods Government of the World by an Inviſible Influence and Power,</hi> &amp;c. But he might have told us, that the Acts, Manner, and Effects of Providence become viſible to us.</p>
               <p>And the diſpoſals of Providence are ſeen, either, 1. In Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Puniſhments.</p>
               <p>Or, 2. In Divine Probations, and Fatherly Corrections and Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Or, 3. In Divine Bleſſings, Mercies, and Deliverances: And all theſe are Perſonal, Domeſtical, or National.</p>
               <p>Now Gods Providence is holy and juſt in all theſe. But ſometimes the Inſtruments are very wicked. Thus proud and cruel men, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95438:12"/>break in pieces Gods people, and afflict his Heritage, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks; tho' they are Gods Rod, or Inſtruments by whom the Lord chaſtiſeth his Servants (which in God is moſt lawful and juſt) I ſay, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men are guilty of the evil of ſin: Becauſe they propound to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſatisfaction of their own malicious and ſpiteful affections. But whoever are the Inſtruments of Gods Providence in Bleſſings, Mercies, Deliverances, in ſuch Acts do well, and deſerve praiſe of all that are not ungrateful. Thus the late Revolution is Gods juſt Judgment and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment on the Papiſts, and all Oppreſſors that joyned with them. But it is an exceeding great mercy, bleſſing, and deliverance to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church, and all Gods faithful Servants. But I ſpare the Dr's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice. He knows the old ſaying, <hi>Dolus latet in generalibus.</hi> God permits evil Inſtruments, but he approves good Inſtruments in ſuch acts.</p>
               <p>It is true alſo as the Dr. ſaith, <hi>That God not only permits, but he doth theſe things. He permits men to do wickedly, but God is the Author of all the Good and Evil, which happens to private perſons, or publick Societies. Surely no Chriſtian doubts of this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then we diſtinguiſh, which the Dr. doth not, and ſay, 1. Evil is from God, who puniſheth, corrects, or chaſtiſeth his Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Good is from God, who defends, delivers, bleſſes, or ſaves his Church. And this is done ordinarily by the free Miniſtries of men.</p>
               <p>And the Queſtion between us is, of theſe Inſtruments, whether they be Evil, or Good, or whether they have done Evil or Good, deſerve well or ill of the Church and Common-wealth?</p>
               <p>Thus to illuſtrate my meaning: I ſay, that <hi>O. C.</hi> and his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates were Uſurpers, Traitors and Murderers; and tho' they had power or ſtrength, yet they had not Power or Authority from God. But King <hi>William</hi> and his Confederates had not only Strength or Power, but alſo had Power or Authority from God to ſave this Church and Kingdom, when we were ſo near ſinking under Popery and Slavery. And this I think is deducible from what the Dr. ſometimes grants. As when he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>The Law of God and Nature muſt take place of all Humane Poſitive Laws and Oaths.</hi> And when he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>Tho' I have as great a Reverence for Princes as any man, I do not think the Right and Intereſt of Princes ſo conſiderable as the Safety and Preſervation of a Nation, and the Lives and Fortunes of all his Subjects.</hi> From whence I infer, that no Poſitive Laws, Oaths, or Prince, in caſe of ſuch Oppreſſions as we groaned under, ought to ſtand in competition with the Preſervation of our Countrey, Liberty, Property and Religion. And conſequently King <hi>William</hi> and his Confederates deſerve Immortal Honour from all Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and good Proteſtants. And if this be not ſound Divinity, I deſire that the Dr. would be pleaſed to beſtow ſome of his Charity upon me, and write another Book to convince thoſe of my Perſwaſion. I wiſh he had free leave given him to try his skill. For tho' I do not pretend
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95438:13"/>to his Learning and Abilities, (and I know that he can teach me many things) nor have I the Opportunity of ſuch Libraries, and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of moſt Judicious Men, yet I have ſtudied this Controverſie, and I never acted in any Affair with a more full and clear Approbation of my own Conſcience than in this Revolution: Or, to uſe the Dr's words in the beginning of his Preface, This I am ſure of, that I never acted with more ſincerity in any Affair of my whole Life, than I have done in this matter, from the beginning to the end; and whether I have ſufficient Reaſon for what I do, I refer to the Tryal of this, and other my Diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>But in ſhort, All Power is of God, and all Power is of the People. All preſervation is of God, and all Preſervation is of our ſelves. All Riches and Honour are of God, and all Riches and Honour are of our ſelves, by our own Induſtry, and good Merit. For tho' we can Merit nothing at Gods Hands, yet we may Merit from Man. Thus, the Hand of the diligent maketh rich, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and the bleſſing of the Lord maketh rich. And ſeeſt thou a Man that is diligent in his buſineſs? he ſhall ſtand before Kings; he ſhall not ſtand before mean Men. This is Gods Cooperation and Concourſe: And God (<hi>quaſi ex pacto coobligat ſe creaturis,</hi> as a Learned Proteſtant Schoolman and Metaphyſician ſpeaks) by Covenant obligeth himſelf with the Creatures, and as it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth that he will help their Acts. And I ſuppoſe the Dr. himſelf doth not imbrace the previous efficacious motion mentioned by the ſtrict Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and of <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus God removes Kings, and ſets up Kings. And this the Dr. will acknowledge, when he recovers himſelf. For he ſaith, p. 13. <hi>Sometimes [a Prince is placed on the Throne by God, and receives his Authority] by the Election of the People; ſometimes by Conqueſt; (which hath been the viſible Original of moſt Governments)</hi> (True ſay I; but Conqueſt makes a Man a Priſoner, not a Subject, till after Conſent and Agreement) <hi>and when any Family is thus advanced to the Throne, it is continued by Succeſſion and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Entails.</hi> But all theſe ways, or any other that can be thought of, are governed and determined by Divine Providence, and the Prince thus advanced is as truely placed in the Throne by God, as if he had been expreſly nominated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Secret or Reaſon of the Drs. obſcurity and confuſion, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, is this, He could not condemn the Inſtruments of Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in this Revolution, out of fear: And he could not juſtifie them, becauſe of his Erroneous Conſcience and Prejudice. And ſo he runs on with a General and Confuſed Diſcourſe of the Diſpoſals of Providence. Juſt as a Quaker, when he knows not what to ſay, will tell you, It is the Light within him that tells him it is ſo as he ſaith. So theſe Men will tell you, that it is Gods Providence: which is very true of all Acts, Means, and Events, good, or evil. But we deſire that Mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95438:13"/>ſhould be ſatisfied, whether the Inſtruments have done well, or ill. But the Dr. will not meddle with this.</p>
               <p>Let us go on. Propoſ. 4. <hi>All Kings</hi> (ſaith the Dr.) <hi>are equally right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with reſpect to God: for thoſe are all rightful Kings, who are placed in the Throne by God, and it is impoſſible there ſhould be a wrong King, unleſs a Man could make himſelf King, whether God will or no,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I take this to be obſcure, and Enthuſiaſtical. Thoſe are all right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Kings who are placed in the Throne by God, ſaith the Dr. True; but how ſhall I know that they are placed in the Throne by God? I ſuppoſe the Dr. will anſwer, When they are throughly Settled in the Throne, as § 2. p. 9. But then ſay I, This is the Election of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſuppoſes a Covenant, Explicite, or Implicite, as before. And this gives Humane and Legal Right. If the Dr. thinks otherwiſe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know of him; for he is ſo cautious, that I cannot poſitively ſay: Sometimes he hath words to this ſenſe; ſometimes not.</p>
               <p>And, I think, it is an odd ſentence to ſay, It is impoſſible there ſhould be a wrong King, unleſs a Man could make himſelf King, whether God will or no, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For God may permit a Man to call himſelf King, who is not King, and his deluded Followers may flatter themſelves, and him alſo: As the late D. of <hi>M.</hi> was called King at <hi>Lyme.</hi> But God never approved of him as King; which I ſuppoſe the Dr. will acknowledge; and yet this was the Diſpoſal of Providence. Let the Dr. diſtinguiſh here, and then he will have an anſwer. And I am of Opinion, that if the P. of <hi>O.</hi> had called Himſelf King, when he entered <hi>Exeter,</hi> or when he marched on without much, if any oppoſition towards <hi>London,</hi> or when he had Poſſeſſion of St. <hi>James</hi>'s, or <hi>Whitehall,</hi> all Engliſhmen had been bound in Conſcience to oppoſe Him, as an Invader of the Liberty of their Countrey. But when by their Repreſentatives they Elected Him King, then all the Duties of Subjects were to be paid to Him. And if I had ten Thouſand Millions of Lives to loſe, I would venture them for this Propoſition, That Law is, or ought to be a Rule to all Men: And that if the King himſelf will go about to deſtroy all Laws, that the Subjects may defend themſelves. And when the Dr. anſwers the Arguments that I have brought in this, and ſome other Diſcourſes by me publiſhed, I ſhall think my ſelf bound to recant. But of this when I come to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. in the next Sect.</p>
               <p>At preſent, I will propoſe a few ſhort Queſtions, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth it appear that a Prince hath Gods Authority, or that he is ſet upon the Throne by the Diſpoſal of Providence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When he hath Actual Poſſeſſion of the Throne.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When hath a Prince Actual Poſſeſſion of the Throne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When he is throughly Settled in his Throne, p. 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. When is his Government throughly Setled?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95438:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When the whole Adminiſtration of the Government, and the whole Power of the Nation is in the Hands of the Prince, <hi>&amp;c. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this laſt Anſwer is intelligible and plain. And thus whoſoever hath Gods Authority or Power, hath it mediately by the Election of the People, or by Covenant, Compact, and Conſent, or Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is an Implicite Covenant; and this is the Diſpoſal of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p>But to begin at the Diſpoſal of Providence, is to ſpeak in the Clouds, and never to give a Rational account, either of the Original, Changes, or Revolutions of Government. In all my Diſcourſe I ſuppoſe not only that God is, but that he hath made us with true Faculties; and ſo we are Reaſonable Creatures, and can give a Rational Account.</p>
               <p>I proceed to Propoſ. 5. The Diſtinction then between a King <hi>de jure,</hi> and a King <hi>de facto,</hi> relates only to Humane Laws, which bind the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but are not neceſſary Rules and Meaſures of Divine Providence. In an Hereditary Kingdom, he is a rightful King, who hath by Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Legal Right to the Crown: And he who hath Poſſeſſion of the Crown, without a Legal Right, is a King <hi>de facto,</hi> that is, is King, but not by Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I imagine that this Diſtinction of a King <hi>de jure,</hi> and a King <hi>de facto,</hi> was invented for another purpoſe; and hath nothing to do in our Controverſie. When the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> laid Claim to the Crown, both by Inheritance and Lineal Succeſſion, the Subjects being in great Perplexity, and many in very great Doubts, Scruples, and Uncertainties, who was the Lineal Succeſſor, it was thought fit to make this Law. He that pretended to Lineal Succeſſion, and had it not, was called a King <hi>de facto.</hi> He that had Lineal Succeſſion was called a King <hi>de jure,</hi> tho' out of Poſſeſſion. But if I were to diſtinguiſh in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Conſcience, as to our Caſe, I would diſtinguiſh thus.</p>
               <p>A King <hi>de jure</hi> is Twofold; either, Firſt, A King by Inheritance: Or, Secondly, A King by Election, tho' he is not the next immediate Heir, nor pretends to be. But in this I humbly ſubmit to the Learned and Judicious Lawyers.</p>
               <p>As for the reſt of this Propoſition, it is of the ſame piece with other Prejudices of the Dr's, and muſt have its Anſwer accordingly. See my other Diſcourſes. And moſt of this Section is of the ſame Nature. The Dr. talks many times of a King having Gods Authority, without Legal Authority. Let him explain, and prove what he ſaith. For I know no Prince that hath Gods Authority, who hath not Legal Authority. When he would clear himſelf of Hobbiſm, (of which I believe he is not guilty) he ſaith well, Power, and nothing elſe, doth not give Right to Dominion, p. 15. But preſently after, he ſeems to write Enthuſiaſtically, and not like a Man guided by Reaſon, and Principles of Nature.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95438:14"/>
               <p>I come now to his Conceſſions. Firſt, <hi>It is evident,</hi> (ſaith the Dr. § 4. p. 23.) <hi>there is no Natural Authority but Paternal, and Patriarchal Authority.</hi> This deſtroys Sir <hi>R. F</hi>'s Principle; and it concerns his hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Followers to conſider it, as I obſerved before. But what the Dr. ſaith immediately after, is more than I can approve of, <hi>That Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies were erected upon the Ruins or great Diminution of it,</hi> &amp;c. For I do not think Monarchy the Ruin or Diminution of Fatherly Authority, but rather the way to preſerve it, and add Perfection to it in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the World. The Dr. might have expreſſed himſelf more wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily. For this ſeems to reflect more upon Monarchy, than the Subjects of a King ought.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hear what he grants, § 4. p. 25. ſpeaking of thoſe who refuſe the Oaths, <hi>If they would examine themſelves for what Reaſon they believe that a King who hath no Right to the Throne, is not ſet up by God, and inveſted with his Authority, they will find, That it muſt ultimately reſolve it ſelf into the Authority of the People to make Kings, which it is unjuſt for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to over-rule and alter:</hi> (<hi>pace tanti viri,</hi> by the Dr's leave, I ſhould ſay, it is not Gods uſual Method and ordinary Providence to over-rule and alter) for a Legal Entail is nothing more than the Authority of the People: And if the People have ſuch an uncontroulable Authority in making Kings, (hold a little, the People cannot do this, when they have Covenanted, ordinarily, but in extream neceſſity) I doubt they will challenge as much Authority to unmake them to. But perhaps the Dr. will ſay, This is <hi>Argumentum ad homines;</hi> and I would not willingly miſrepreſent him. As for his Anſwer to the Objection, which I find, p. 26. I know not what to make of it, it is pure Enthuſiaſm, I think: I cannot meaſure it by any Rules of Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He grants very honeſtly, p. 27. <hi>That when ever a People have a good King,</hi> (as ſurely, ſay I, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> are a good King and Queen) <hi>it is both their Duty and Intereſt to defend Him: And if they be not miſled by the Cunning and Artifice of ill Men, they will certainly do ſo.</hi> But if they have a very bad one, that notoriouſly violates their Rights, and breaks the Conſtitution upon which Himſelf ſtands, and ſtrikes at the deareſt things they have, their Religion Eſtabliſhed by Law, and their Properties, I doubt the Caſe may be altered. And tho' every Body will not ſpeak it out, yet moſt may ſay in their Hearts, Let him go, if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not defend Himſelf. It is enough in Conſcience patiently to bear ſo bad a Prince, but a little too much to venture their Lives and Fortunes to keep him in the Throne to oppreſs them. This is againſt Reaſon and Nature, and I know no Law of God which requires it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I wiſh with all my heart that this Conſideration, and other Arguments of the Dr's. may prevail with the moſt Reverend Father in God, the late Arch-Biſhop, and the Right Reverend the Biſhops, who have not taken the Oaths to their preſent Majeſties, I believe, out of pure Conſcience, tho' erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95438:15"/>and full of prejudice. And I have often wondered, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Clergy, who but a little before did ſo violently oppoſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s proceedings (out of the like conſcientious prejudice, as I believe) did on a ſudden take the Oaths. This ſeems to me, to ſhew that our Caſe wanted but a little conſideration, and men might eaſily lay aſide their prejudices, in ſo bleſſed and deſirable a Change.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Dr. grants, <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>That the Laws of God and Nature muſt take place of all Humane Poſitive Laws and Oaths.</hi> Hence I infer, that the Dr. cannot deny Self-preſervation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He grants, <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>That it is unreaſonable to expound the Oath to ſuch a ſenſe, as no man would have taken it in had it been expreſſed: No, no man in his wits would take it for the beſt Prince that ever ſwayed the Scepter.</hi> Then ſuch an Oath, or Promiſe, or Declaration, could not intend to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtroy Self-preſervation, Liberty, and Property.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Dr. grants, <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>We are not bound to defend the King againſt Law, or when he ſubverts the Laws, und Liberties, and the Legal Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion of the Kingdom, by Illegal Methods:</hi> Or, as he ſaith preſently after, <hi>by the exerciſe of an Illegal and Arbitrary Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. He ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>Certainly this was not the Intention of the Oath, to fight for their King againſt their Countrey.</hi> For an Oath to fight for the King, doth not oblige us to fight againſt our Countrey, which is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, as to fight againſt our King.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He owns the preſervation of the whole Kingdom is before the Prince, <hi>p.</hi> 33. in theſe words; <hi>Tho' I have as great a Reverence for Princes as any man, I do not think the Right and Intereſt of any Prince ſo conſiderable, as the Safety and Preſervation of the Nation, and the Lives and Fortunes of all his Subjects.</hi> I am ſure, we, who are for Defenſive Arms, cannot ſay more than this.</p>
               <p n="9">9. I leave the Teachers of Paſſive Obedience and Non-Reſiſtance to anſwer his Arguments, <hi>p.</hi> 36. or elſe I hope they will take the Oaths. I have ſpoken my thoughts of this matter. As for Biſhop <hi>Overals</hi> Convocation-Book, I do not love many words, I have ſpoken my mind.</p>
               <p n="10">10. This ſeems very hard, that when God hath actually delivered us, we muſt refuſe our deliverance, <hi>p.</hi> 38. And I add, it ſeems very hard that the Clergy, who receive moſt benefit by this deliverance, (if in heart they love the Proteſtant Religion) ſhould not honour the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverers.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Dr. agrees to what Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> tells us, <hi>That the End of Civil Government, and of that Obedience which is due to it, is the Safety and Tranquillity of Humane Societies; and therefore whatever is neceſſary and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to this End, becomes our Duty: for the End preſcribes the Means.</hi> Hence I infer the lawfulneſs of Defenſive Arms in ſome caſe; becauſe Humane Societies under a Tyrannical Prince, who Rules Arbitrarily, cannot be ſafe. I beſeech the Dr. ſeriouſly to conſider this, and examine throughly whether it doth not neceſſarily follow.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95438:15"/>
               <p>And before I end this Section, I muſt deſire the Dr. to reconcile ſome of his Aſſertions.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>hath been very careful to inſtruct her Children in their duty to Princes; to obey their Laws, and ſubmit to their Power, and not to reſist, tho' very injuriouſly oppreſſed; and thoſe who renounce theſe Principles, renounce the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England. But ſhe hath withal taught, <hi>That all Sovereign Princes receive their Power and Authority from God; and therefore every Prince, who is ſetled in the Throne, is to be obeyed and reverenced as Gods Minister, and not to be reſisted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And here I obſerve that the Dr. chargeth the Non-ſwearing Biſhops, as well as thoſe who joyned with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as rejecting the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Well; let the Dr. and his Party be the only true Church of <hi>England-men,</hi> if he can diſprove what I have now and elſewhere ſaid. He grants, <hi>That whoſoever is ſetled in the Throne, hath Gods Authority, and must not be reſiſted.</hi> But <hi>p.</hi> 25, 26. in anſwering an Objection, That this makes the Prince loſe his Right by being notoriouſly injured, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he tells us, <hi>The Providence of God removes Kings, and ſets up Kings, but alters no Legal Rights, nor forbids thoſe who are diſpoſſeſſed of them, to recover their Right when they can,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and doth not divest the diſpoſſeſſed Prince of his Legal Right and Claim, nor forbid him to endeavour to recover his Throne, nor forbid thoſe who are under no Obligation to the Prince in Poſſeſſion, to aſſist the diſpoſſeſſed Prince to recover his Legal Right,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor hinder him from Claiming it, when he finds his opportunity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would here know of the Dr. who they are that are under no Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to the Prince in Poſſeſſion, and ſo may aſſiſt the diſpoſſeſſed Prince? Are they Domeſtick Subjects, or Forreign Enemies? What? may the late King with a good Conſcience invade <hi>England</hi> with an Army of French-men to recover that which the Dr. calls his Legal Right? I believe the Dr. to be an honeſt man, and that he hath no Plot or Deſign; but let him ſee the tendency of his Argument.</p>
               <p>I ſhould anſwer the Objection thus; The diſpoſſeſſed Prince is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, or evil. If he is a good Prince, and hath not oppreſſed his Subjects, his caſe is hard, and very calamitous, and much to be pitied; but he muſt ſubmit to Divine Providence, and Gods Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Correction or Probation. And this is a difficulty in Providence, as the Dr's. phraſe is; according to the account of all Philoſphers, <hi>Cur bonis malè?</hi> But if his Subjects have ſtood by him with their Lives and Fortunes, and are conquered, and have ſetled the Government of the Conqueror, either by a General Aſſembly, or by Univerſal Submiſſion, Promiſe, Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are excuſable, and the King ſo forced into Baniſhment, in Conſcience cannot require their Allegiance. If the Prince be evil, and hath oppreſſed his Subjects in a high meaſure,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95438:16"/>then he forfeiteth his Legal Right, and it is transferred on another King for the publick good. But I pray God this may never befal the Royal Family again, while the Sun and Moon endureth. But furely the Nobility, Gentry, Clergy and Commons had Reaſon and Conſcience to defend themſelves againſt the Tyranny of Jeſuits, and other evil Counſellors, who tempted the King to be ungrateful, and ſeek the Ruine of their Religion and Properties.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>p.</hi> 14. The Dr. ſaith, <hi>He who hath Poſſeſſion of the Crown without a Legal Right,</hi> (that is, as he means, a Succeſſive Right) <hi>is a King</hi> de facto, that is, <hi>is King, but not by Law.</hi> And yet <hi>p.</hi> 63. he ſaith, <hi>The Law requires us to own him for our Sovereign.</hi> Let the Dr. reconcile this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>Animadverſions on Section 4.</head>
               <p>I have before anſwered the Dr's Obſervation, <hi>That the Scripture hath given us no Direction in this caſe, but to ſubmit, and pay all Obedience of Subjects unto the preſent Powers.</hi> It makes no diſtinction, that ever I could find, between a Rightful King, and an Uſurper, between a King whom we muſt; and whom we muſt not obey. See Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions on Sect. 2.</p>
               <p>And now I come to that famous Text of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. And here the Reverend Dr. ſtill owns Paſſive Obedience and Non-Reſiſtance. And he tells us in his Preface, <hi>That he hath renounced no Principle that ever he taught, except one in the caſe of Reſiſtance, p.</hi> 128, &amp;c. which is the only material paſſage he knows any reaſon to retract in that Book, to wit, that when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>All Power is of God,</hi> he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth only Legal Powers.</p>
               <p>Now I think the Dr. hath had the ill Fortune to adhere to one of the worſt Principles, and renounce one of the beſt Principles, that ever he taught in Government.</p>
               <p>And that I may prove this, it muſt come to my Turn to ſuppoſe. And here I ſhall premiſe the Dr's Words in the end of his Preface, <hi>They who underſtand what belongs to Diſputes of this nature, know very well that the ſhorteſt way to bring the matter to an Iſſue, is to put the Caſe at the worſt that can be ſuppoſed; becauſe this gives ſo much greater force and advantage to the Argument, when it is ſuited to thoſe, who are moſt ſtrongly prejudiced [againſt the Lawfulneſs of Defenſive Arms in any Caſe.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In managing this Argument,</hi> (as the Dr. goes on) <hi>it is neceſſary to reaſon upon ſuppoſition of the moſt Illegal and greateſt Oppreſſions: And it may be I may meet with ſome Readers, as may charge me for ſo doing, with unchriſtian Behaviour, and clowniſh Irreverence towards a calamitous Prince, which I am very ſure, I am far from intending to do.</hi> I ſay, as I ſaid at firſt, Sacred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95438:16"/>Majeſty laid in the duſt requires our Tears: Our Religion, and our Laws revived require our Joy. This premiſed, I offer a Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the Late King was reſolved to Rule by a Standing Army: Suppoſe he had Suſpended all the Biſhops, as well as the Biſhop of <hi>London:</hi> Suppoſe he had turned all the Nobility out of their Freeholds, as well as the Preſident, and Fellows of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge: Suppoſe he had ſet up an Illegal High Commiſſion Court: Suppoſe he had Tryed all the Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> for their Lives, as well as the Seven Innocent Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: Suppoſe he had Cloſeted all the Nobility, as well as he did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to over-awe their Votes in Parliament: Suppoſe he had given Power to all the Diſſenters, and Sectaries to preach in our Pulpits, as well as in private Meetings: Suppoſe all the Members of his Privy Council had been Jeſuits, and Bigotted Papiſts, as well as Father <hi>Petre, Tyrcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> &amp;c. Suppoſe he had Suſpended all the Clergy in <hi>England</hi> for not Reading the Illegal Declaration in Churches: Suppoſe he had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Officers of his Standing Army to Plunder our Houſes, and cut our Throats. And now I think that I have almoſt ſuppoſed the worſt that I can ſuppoſe: And verily I tremble to ſuppoſe this. I will make but one Suppoſition more. Suppoſe that by teaching this Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance the Late King might be tempted to bring in his Religion by theſe Illegal and Horrid means: And thereby not only loſe his Crown and Dignity, but hazard the Damnation of his Soul, without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet the Authors Doctrine is, <hi>Subjects muſt not reſiſt.</hi> And he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, eſpecially St.</hi> Paul <hi>in</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>taught this Doctrine, when he ſaith,</hi> Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Damnation. No doubt but this is very edifying Doctrine. This was moſt irreſiſtible Rhetorick to the Senate, and People of <hi>Rome</hi> (the freeſt People of the World) to turn Chriſtians. For then, tho' their Philoſophers taught them, that they might defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt Tyrants by the Law of Nature, yet, they muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Liberties of their Countrey: If they do, they muſt never be happy hereafter. This is an invincible Argument to any Jealous <hi>Roman,</hi> or Wiſe <hi>Grecian,</hi> to imbrace Chriſtianity. Is not this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine againſt all Gods Attributes, his Goodneſs, his Juſtice, his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as well as the Predeſtinarian Doctrine is ſaid to be? What! hath God left his poor innocent Creatures, I mean Legally innocent, to be a prey to Lions? <hi>Credat Judaeus Apella, non ego.</hi> And here I may uſe the Dr's words, (for I confeſs my ſtile is not ſo Elegant) p. 40. According to theſe Principles Humane Societies in ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions (I muſt ſay Male-Adminiſtrations) cannot be preſerved without ſin: For if all Men did their Duty, they muſt all be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95438:17"/>Now, I believe it will be hard to perſwade any conſidering Men, that that which in ſuch a Caſe is neceſſary to preſerve a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is a ſin: And that which will infallibly deſtroy it, is a Duty and Virtue: If we allow the Safety and Preſervation of Humane Societies, to be the great Law of all. And I will add the Dr's words, § 1. p. 3. <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> The Doctrine of Reſiſtance in ſome Caſe may ſtartle ſome Men at firſt, before they have well conſidered it. But every one at firſt ſight muſt acknowledge, that it is ſo much for the Eaſe and Safety of Subjects in all Male-Adminiſtrations and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Oppreſſion, (which ſometimes happen) what the Generality of Mankind, from an inward Principle of Self-preſervation, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways done, and will always do, that they have reaſon to wiſh it to be true, and to be glad to ſee it well proved. And p. 18. Theſe Principles are ſo very uſeful, eſpecially in all Innovations in Church, or State, that Subjects have great Reaſon to wiſh them true, and to examine over again thoſe ſtrict Principles of Loyalty, which if pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued to their juſt Conſequence, muſt unavoidably in ſome Junctures, Sacrifice whole Kingdoms, at leaſt all Subjects, who pretend to this degree and kind of Loyalty and Conſcience, to the Tyranny of Evil Counſellors, or Male-Adminiſtration of their Prince. And once more I will borrow the Dr's words, p. 44. (for I cannot uſe ſo good) Since then ſuch Male-Adminiſtrations will happen, ſuch Principles as muſt diſſolve Humane Society, when ſuch Male-Adminiſtration hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, or expoſe the moſt innocent and conſciencious Men to the greateſt Sufferings, without ſerving any good end by them, cannot be true: For the End of Government is the Preſervation of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies, and therefore that can be no good Principle of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which in the greateſt Male-Adminiſtration, if purſued, muſt Ruin the moſt excellent, true, and harmleſs Subjects, who deſire nothing but to live according to Law, and ſave their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, conveyed to them by their Anceſtors. Paſſive Obedience in ſuch Caſe is to make all Mankind the Slaves and Properties of Princes: As if all Men were made for Princes, not Princes for the Government of Men, p. 45.</p>
               <p>I know not but that a Barbarous and Savage Prince, as <hi>Tyberius,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, That there paſſed no day, no not ſo much as any Feſtival and Religious Holy-day, without the Execution and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſome. Or as <hi>Caligula,</hi> who being highly diſpleaſed upon a time with the multitude, <hi>Would to God</hi> (quoth he) <hi>that the People of</hi> Rome <hi>had but one Neck,</hi> meaning to chop them off at one blow: And ſaid, <hi>Let them hate me, ſo they fear me.</hi> Or as <hi>Nero,</hi> who is reported to ſay, <hi>Let the whole Earth be on Fire, while I live.</hi> I ſay ſuch cruel Tyrants may poſſibly be well pleaſed with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95438:17"/>of Non-reſiſtance. But ſurely no good and wiſe Prince, who would have the Affections of his Subjects, doth deſire that ſuch Doctrine ſhould be taught. The Great and Noble Spirit of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar,</hi> or the Courage and Valour, together with the Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and Mercy of a <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> or the Impartial Adminiſtration of Juſtice in a <hi>Trajan,</hi> would deteſt and loath ſuch a ſottiſh, bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and unnatural Principle. And nothing can make a Prince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage it, but a Deſign upon his People, or to reduce them to Popery and Slavery, or to Rule Tyrannically, that is, both Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Uneaſily. St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſtood upon his Priviledge againſt the Magiſtrate, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.37. Paul <hi>ſaid unto them, They have beaten us openly uncondemned, being</hi> Romans, <hi>and have caſt us into Priſon, and now do they thruſt us out privily? Nay verily, but let them come themſelves, and fetch us out.</hi> It is a moſt excellent and prevailing Motive for the Saviour of Mankind, and his choſen Apoſtles, to uſe, to tell them, that if they will be his Diſciples, in ſome Caſe they muſt become Slaves. If they ſave their Countrey, and defend themſelves againſt Violence and Oppreſſion, (which they cannot but do, as Senſible and Reaſonable Creatures) they are certainly Damned. This verily is to become Fools that they may be wiſe to Salvation, in another Senſe than St. <hi>Paul</hi> meant it.</p>
               <p>And now let us hear what the Dr. ſaith to us about <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>To ſay the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh of Lawful Powers, is</hi> gratis dictum, <hi>for there is no Evidence of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is Evidence of it; and the Evidence or Reaſon of it, is this; Neither God, nor Man gives Authority to any man to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Innocent. Therefore the Innocent in reſiſting Illegal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, reſiſt no Authority; Nor do no evil, forbidden by God, or Man. See my Anſwer to the Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience, in the beginning.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith the Dr. <hi>The Criticiſm between</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>will not do; for they both ſignifie the ſame thing in Scripture, either Force and Power, or Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Some Paſſive-Obedience men think this unanſwerable: But ſurely the Dr. cannot think the Divines of our Perſwaſion ſo weak, as to lay the ſtrength of the Argument upon a Word or Criticiſm. But firſt they give a Reaſon, as before, and then to illuſtrate their Argument, uſe the words, as Modern Criticks ſay, they are moſt commonly uſed in our days. The Apoſtle doth not ſay, <hi>All Power,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, Strength is of God; but <hi>All Power,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or Lawful Power, is of God; implying, that it is not he that is the ſtrongeſt man, hath Gods Authority, as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſaith; neither hath any Oppreſſor in the Act of Oppreſſion; neither are we
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95438:18"/>required not to reſiſt ſuch Acts of Oppreſſion. But I obſerve how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that he ſaith not a word to thoſe Criticks, who ſay, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Powers that be,</hi> that is, the True (or Lawful) Powers. But I would not have the Dr. think, that our Divines lay the ſtieſs of ſo great a cauſe upon Criticiſms; but they may be plain Illuſtrations.</p>
               <p>The Dr. goes on, <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>Why ſhould we think the Apostle here intends a distinction unknown to Scripture? Had there been any ſuch Rule before given, To ſubmit to Lawful Powers, but not to ſubmit to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers, there had been ſome pretence for understanding St.</hi> Paul's All Powers, <hi>of all Legal Power; but there being nothing like this any where elſe in Scripture, if he had intended any ſuch distinction, he ought to have ſaid it in expreſs words, or elſe no body could reaſonably have understood him to intend this Precept of ſubjection to the Higher Powers, only of the Powers that had Legal Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not bound, neither was he ſent to teach the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Political Government, but he ſuppoſeth them to know this by the Cuſtoms of their Countrey, and he tells them, They muſt ſubmit, and not reſiſt; for <hi>all Power is of God.</hi> Chriſtians, as well as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, or Jews, muſt obey Authority. But he doth not ſay, that Uſurped Power or Strength is of God, and to be ſubmitted to. And though the Dr. ſaith, <hi>There is nothing like this any where elſe in Scripture, which is</hi> gratis dictum, yet other Learned Divines ſay, that the Apoſtle means this, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. When he ſaith, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake, whether to the King as Supream.</hi> Hence they collect, and I think truly, That the Donation of the Power is of God, and the Deſignation of the Perſon, or Limitation and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the Power is of Man, tho' it is alſo the diſpoſal of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. I have ſaid in another Diſcourſe, God and Man in theſe Acts are not oppoſite, but ſubordinate. God is the firſt Cauſe; Man is the ſecond Cauſe. The Prince that receives Authority from Man, receives it from God alſo, tho' mediately by Man; and is Gods Miniſter and a Ruler, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4.</p>
               <p>The Dr. proceeds; <hi>Then in order to the fulfilling of this precept, it would be neceſſary for Subjects to exarmine the Titles of Princes, and to that end to be well skill'd in Hiſtory, and the Laws of a Nation, and to be able to judge between a pretended and real Right,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> And ſurely it is not ſo difficult a thing to know who is our Prince, as the Dr. would make it. It is ſo eaſie, that every Subject in <hi>England,</hi> as far as ever I heard, never doubted that the late King <hi>James</hi> was the lawful King of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> And there needs no great skill in Hiſtory and Law to know this. And as for the Revolution, when we are bound in Conſcience to obey another King, there needs no Hiſtory to tell us, what we have ſeen and heard. And the Reverend Dr. will tell
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95438:18"/>us, when the Government is ſetled, <hi>p.</hi> 9. Suppoſe the greateſt uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that you can ſuppoſe, the Conſciences of men would not be more perplexed, than you have perplexed them at this day: And therefore you need not have ſaid, <hi>Let any man judge in what perplexities this ſenſe of the Apoſtles Precept would involve the Conſciences of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Dr. hath a great deal more to the ſame purpoſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcants at large. To which I anſwer in general, That if St. <hi>Paul</hi> had taught us Politicks in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. I ſhould have thought it very ſtrange. Men muſt learn Politicks from the Laws of Reaſon, and the common Prudence and Experience of Mankind.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the Great Turk in a Paſſion, or upon a ſmall Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſhould draw his Scymeter or Sword, to kill ſome Eminent Nobleman of his Court, and the Nobleman ſhould defend his Life by force of Arms, and by Skill or Strength ſhould diſarm his great Lord and Maſter, and eſcape for his Life. In this caſe I ſay, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion and Conſcience will juſtifie the Innocent Nobleman, and will tell the Great Turk, that he ought to give God thanks in ſuch like words as <hi>David</hi> did, when <hi>Abigail</hi> by her wiſdom pacified his wrath, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God, who ſent thee this day to meet me; And bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſſed be thou, who haſt kept me this day from ſhedding blood.</hi> I ſhould never read the Scriptures, nor any Hiſtory or Law-book, to tell me, who is my King, no more than I would to tell me, who is my Father and Mother. I like a Fool have all my days preſumed without Book, with my Fellow-ſubjects, and with my Brethren and Siſters, who is my King, and who is my Father and Mother; and have honoured and obeyed them according to the fifth Commandment. Such reaſoning is unworthy of the profound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi> If the Dr. pleaſeth, I would deſire him to write a Book to teach Children what are their Names, and who are their God-fathers and God-mothers, before we Catechize them any more. For, is it not a very hard thing to know all theſe things? See how prejudice blinds the Eyes of pious and wiſe men.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, that when there is a competition for the Crown, or when Impoſture may be reaſonably ſuſpected, or in the like extraordinary caſe, then the Subjects may become Sceptics. But then we have a Privy Council, and a Parliament, to examine, judge, and determine. But otherwiſe, I am perſaded that there was not one of ten thouſand, that ever doubted, whether King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was the true Heir, and rightful King, or King <hi>James</hi> the Second.</p>
               <p>But let us hear the Dr's. Objection, <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>If the choice and conſent of the People makes a Prince, then no man is a Subject, but he who conſents to be ſo; For the major Vote cannot include my conſent, unleſs I pleaſe: That is the Effect of Law and Compact, or Force, not of Nature. If Subjects give
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95438:19"/>their Prince Authority, they may take it away again, if they pleaſe. There can be no Irreſiſtible Authority derived from the People: For if Authority be wholly derived from them, who ſhall hinder them from taking it away when they ſee fit? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe Principles, there can be no Hereditary Monarchy: One Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration can only chuſe for themſelves; their Poſterity have as much right to chuſe as they had.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Dr. owns, That if the Lineal Succeſſion ſhould fail, then the People muſt chuſe a Prince; and this hinders not Hereditary Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy. No more doth it in ſuch an extraordinary caſe as our preſent caſe is. And the Dr. himſelf ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>A Legal Entail is nothing more than the Authority of the People;</hi> tho' here he ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe Principles there can be no Hereditary Monarchy.</hi> Let him reconcile theſe. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath ſetled the Succeſſion.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith the Dr. <hi>Every Subject muſt conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is thought a mighty <hi>Goliath,</hi> but I think it a poor, weak Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I have elſewhere ſhewed, that the meek, wiſe, and ever-renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hooker,</hi> foundeth all Government in Covenant, ſo that I am not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And ſurely it is not required in our Conſtitution, that every individual perſon conſent explicitly to Acts of Parliament, but the major Vote includes all. And there is nothing more common in the World, either in Political, or Sacred Affairs, than for a Father, or Guardian, or God-father, or Friend, or Relation, to engage for a Child. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 29, 10, 11. If it were any other perſon, I ſhould be afraid, would turn Anabaptiſt, or at leaſt a Puritan, and write a Book againſt God-fathers. In theſe Caſes an Implicite Covenant is fully ſufficient. If the whole Kingdom conſiſts of ſuch who were Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their Parents, that Elected the Prince, and agreed that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhould be Hereditary, this in Conſcience binds them: Tho' they make no Perſonal and Vocal Expreſſion of their Conſent and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Fathers did. I imagine that upon ſecond Thoughts the Dr. will have no mind to oppoſe this, and therefore I ſay no more.</p>
               <p>But the Dr. ſaith, <hi>That if Subjects give their Prince Authority, then they may take it away again, if they pleaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All Subjects are bound in Conſcience to ſtand to their Covenant, Agreement, Promiſe, and Oath. And here whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to themſelves Damnation. This is Rebellion, ſuppoſing a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom not univerſally oppreſſed. And this ſecures the Prince, as well as the Providence of God, in the Dr's unintelligible Notion.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline"> But this is to ſay, God, as well as Man, is confined to Humane Laws in making Kings, p. 25.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95438:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I ſuppoſe the Dr. living among ſuch an Honourable Society of Lawyers, hath heard of being tryed by God and the Countrey: And ſo the King and Queen may be made by God and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. God feeds us, but we muſt put Meat in our Mouths. God Clothes us, but we muſt put on our Clothes. God doth what we do, when we uſe the Means appointed by God. And when the Dr. is in a reaſoning Humour, he will tell us, that there is no doubt but ſeveral Governments have been begun by, and Originally derived from the Choice and Conſent of the People, p. 23. but ſtill it is God, who by his Providence advanceth Men to the Throne. But of this before.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe who advance Conqueſt, I have ſpoken my Mind formerly. And I add, that when the whole Community, be it by the Sword, is ſubdued, (as the Jews were by <hi>Caeſar</hi>) and have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Subjection, and own the Authority of the Conqueror, and he promiſeth them Protection, I grant this gives the Conqueror Humane Right and Title, as well as Gods Authority. For he holds his Crown (as ſome ſpeak) <hi>jure Gentium &amp; conceſſu Gentium.</hi> But if the P. of <hi>O.</hi> did Conquer <hi>England,</hi> againſt which he declared, and acted nothing like a Conqueror in any part of the Nation, where his Army Marched, but every where like a Saviour and Deliverer. I ſay, if the P. of <hi>O.</hi> did Conquer the Nation, the Princeſs of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> did not. And Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Title can be no other way (God ſave Her Majeſty, for I am Her moſt Loyal Subject and Servant) but by the Election of the People in Convention, and now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Act of Parliament: Which I deſire all Conſcientious Men to conſider.</p>
               <p>Finally, As for Submiſſion, that is an Implicite Covenant, as I have ſhewed, and muſt be kept. So that (tho' the Dr. cannot, yet with all, or the moſt Judicious Philoſophers, Schoolmen, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Divines) I can ſee where to fix the Foundation of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that is in the Agreement of the People: And this is the ordinary Diſpoſal of Providence. But let it be by the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Conſent of the People: Or by Conqueſt, and ſo by After-Covenant: Or by Submiſſion, which is an Implicite After-Covenant: Or by continued Uſurpation, as the Dr. ſpeaks, which ſtill is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon After-Covenant and Promiſe, all theſe are the Diſpoſals of Providence. So that the Dr. very weakly (for I do not believe he doth it craftily) gives only the General Cauſe, which no Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. But we deſire to know, what is <hi>(cauſa ſecunda, proxima, &amp; particularis)</hi> the ſecond, next, and particular Cauſe (as the Schools ſpeak) of this Revolution and Government.</p>
               <p>And the Reaſon is, either we have done very well, or very ill
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95438:20"/>in joining with the P. of <hi>O.</hi> And we would gladly convince the Dr. or any Man elſe, that we have hazarded all that is dear to Man, Virtuouſly and Honourably, to preſerve Gods true Religion and Worſhip as by Law Eſtabliſhed, to ſave the Engliſh Monarchy from the Uſurpations of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and to continue the Liberties of our Native Countrey.</p>
               <p>The Providence of God is no Rule, or Reaſon, or Meaſure of our Duty: But the Law of God and Nature, and the Laws of the Land, when they contradict not theſe. And the Dr. will tell us ſo, when he thinks of it, p. 32. The Divine Providence hath Ways and Methods of removing Kings and Setting up Kings, which we are not aware of, nor concern'd to know, becauſe it is no part of our Duty.</p>
               <p>To ſum up all this, In this Revolution ſome talk of Deſertion and Abdication: Some of Conqueſt: Some of Gods Providence, as the Dr. and ſome of the Election of the People.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to Deſertion and Abdication, whether the Late King did in a proper and ſtrict ſenſe Abdicate the Kingdom is a matter that I need not diſpute, but ſurely the Convention did well to take this into Conſideration, that the Kingdom was left without any Order or Government, in a very troubleſom time. But ſuppoſing that it was a proper and ſtrict Abdication, this doth not make the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>England.</hi> This muſt be ſome other way.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to Conqueſt. And, 3. As to Gods Providence, I have ſaid enough to ſatisfie any Conſciencious, and wiſe Man, who will lay aſide Prejudice and Prepoſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>And therefore, 4. I am fully ſatisfied in my own Conſcience, and will diſpute the Caſe with any Learned and Conſciencious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, that it can be juſtified no other way, but by the Election of the People in Convention.</p>
               <p>As for the Examples of <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> and <hi>Joaſh,</hi> and <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and <hi>Jehu,</hi> I think there may be a better Account given, than the Dr. gives: But this is nothing to the main Controverſie between him, and us. That concerns the Non-Swearers.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only give you a familiar Simile or Example out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Election of a King, tho' it doth not <hi>quadrare in omnibus;</hi> it is not (nor needs be) fitted in all Circumſtances to the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt Book of <hi>Sam.</hi> chap. 8. The People of Iſrael deſire a King. (Then it follows, they had none before.) Whereupon <hi>Samuel</hi> told them his Meſſage from God, and at laſt yielded to the importunity of the People. And he called all the People, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. that is, All the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95438:20"/>Heads, Elders, and Princes of the People; a great Convention, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Aſſembly of the Nation. And they choſe <hi>Saul.</hi> And all the People ſhouted, and ſaid, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi> And thoſe whoſe Hearts God had touched went with him. And they that deſpiſed him, were called Children of <hi>Belial.</hi> And I ſhall only add <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Admonition and Counſel, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 24, 25. <hi>Only fear the Lord, and ſerve him in truth with all your heart: for conſider how great things he hath done for you. But if ye ſhall ſtill do wickedly, ye ſhall be conſumed, both ye and your King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know that there are two Prejudices (as the Dr. ſpeaks in like caſe) rather than Objections againſt this Truth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. This will not pleaſe the King, and Royal Family.</item>
                  <item>2. This occaſions Subjects to Rebel, when they think fit.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. This will not pleaſe the King, and Royal Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are confident that this is an Inſinuation of weak Spirits, and directly contrary to the Great and Heroick Deſigns of their Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, and their Impartial Adminiſtrations of Juſtice; and God forbid we ſhould do any thing juſtly meriting the loſs of Their Majeſties Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and their Hearts confiding in us. <hi>I</hi> am ſure that the pleading for our Liberties, is no Prejudice to the Kings Crown, or Prerogatives. Why ſhould not our Soveraign look upon us with Reſpect, when we pay him all Legal Obedience out of Conſcience, and venture our Lives and Fortunes in defence of his Crown and Dignity, as well as of our Laws, and Properties? Why may not we hope for Preferment, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Commendation, as well as thoſe who never practiſe what they teach? When I have lived to ſee their Senſes too much for their ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Divinity. But however we fare in this World, I am of Opinion, that a King ſhould do Juſtice, a Prieſt ſhould teach Truth, and a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſhould Fight for a good Cauſe, and leave the Succeſs to God. The Happineſs of a Kingdom is in a Princes Ruling as a Father, and Subjects obeying out of Love, rather than meer neceſſity.</p>
               <p>Obj. 2. <hi>This occaſions Subjects to Rebel, when they think fit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I ſay, beſides what I have formerly written, that the Doctrine of Non-Aſſiſtance, which is now become common, is as bad, if not worſe than our Doctrine of Reſiſtance in ſome Caſe. Now the Dr. owns the former, p. 50. ſaying, <hi>Thus far I think the Subjects may be very guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, who do not drive the King away, but only ſuffer him quietly (to be driven away, or) to eſcape out of his Kingdom: for this is no Rebellion, no Reſiſtance, but only Non-aſſiſtance, which may be very innocent: For there are ſome Caſes, wherein Subjects are not bound to aſſiſt their Prince, and if ever there were ſuch a Caſe this is it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I grant Non-Aſſiſtance and Reſiſtance are not the ſame in all caſes: I grant we are not bound to aſſiſt our King in Illegal Commands: But I ſhould think, that if we may not reſiſt him in his Illegal and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Commands, we ought in Conſcience to aſſiſt him in his Legal
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95438:21"/>Commands, eſpecially in the preſervation of his Perſon, Crown and Dignity. And I am ſure that the late King would have called this a Seditious and Rebellious Doctrine, as well as ours. But thus the poor King was cheated. And the Dr. may ſay, as well as think in his heart, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>Let him go, if he cannot defend himſelf.</hi> Well; I commend the Dr. in this caſe, for Teaching Subjects to ſleep in a whole skin. But in troth I think, it is more plain dealing, and the King had better be told, that in the ſame caſe they will not aſſiſt him, they will reſiſt, that is, in caſe of Univerſal Oppreſſion.</p>
               <p>I will ſuppoſe for once, that <hi>David</hi> was againſt Defenſive Arms and Reſiſtance in any caſe; and upon this ſuppoſition, let us hear his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Reſolution, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.15, 16. David <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Abner, <hi>Art not thou a valiant man? and who is like unto thee in</hi> Iſrael? <hi>Wherefore then haſt thou not kept thy Lord the King? for there came one of the people in to deſtroy the King thy Lord. This thing is not good that thou haſt done: As the Lord liveth, ye are worthy to die, becauſe ye have not kept your Maſter the Lords Anointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abner</hi> might have replied to <hi>David,</hi> (if he had been taught by the Dr.) Sir, the King is in purſuit of you, when you are innocent; and that illegally, cruelly, cauſleſly, maliciouſly; and therefore tho' I muſt not reſiſt, I may not aſſiſt, nor ſee your innocent blood ſhed. Take my Maſter, Lord, and King, and do what you will with him. Here I muſt deſire the Dr. to reflect upon his Conſcience in the fear of God. And I dare appeal to the Judgment of any moderate, conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and learned Papiſt, or to the Judgment of any indifferent man in the World, if our Doctrine be not as honeſt as this. In this caſe Non-Aſſiſtance is as bad as Reſiſtance; for the Prince muſt certainly, infallibly, and inevitably fall into the hands of his Adverſaries, with this aggravation, That thoſe he truſted deceived him.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe we may conſider that diſtinction of the Efficient Cauſe mentioned by the School-men. It is either, 1. Phyſical Or, 2. Moral. The Phyſical Cauſe is that which hath a real influx to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Effect, or that which truly, and of it ſelf contributes to the Being of the Effect. The Moral Cauſe is that, which tho' it doth not really operate in producing the Effect, yet it is ſuch <hi>(in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Moris)</hi> in order to Manners, as they ſay, as if it really conferred Being to the Effect; and that becauſe the Effect that follows is no leſs imputable to it, than if it had produced the Effect by a real influx; ſuch are cauſes conſulting, commanding, and not hindering, when they ought to hinder. But I have ſufficiently laſhed this Doctrine elſewhere.</p>
               <p>As for the reſt of the Book, it is either what we grant, or what hath been already anſwered, or contains the Dr's. Arguments to perſwade the Clergy, that have not taken the Oaths. And I ſee no reaſon why the Arguments ſhould not prevail with them, if they will lay aſide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95438:21"/>But I believe the Dr. may Preach Paſſive Obedience, and Non-Reſiſtance upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. long enough, before he will gain one rational and conſidering man. For the Male-adminiſtration of the late unhappy King, and the Tyranny, Pride, and Inſolence of the Jeſuits, inſtead of frighting them out of their ſenſes, have frighted the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into their ſenſes, that they will rather believe they merit Salvation (if the Proteſtant Faith allowed it) than that they are guilty of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, which, the Apoſtle ſaith, ſhall receive Damnation, for joyning with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and his Confederates, in this Revolution.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I ſhall conclude with theſe three Propoſitions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In our Caſe Defenſive Arms were lawful.</p>
               <p n="2">2. King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> with their true Friends, can be juſtified no other way.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Doctrine, as I have explained it, is neither contrary to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor more prejudicial or dangerous to Monarchy, than any other Principle; as will appear, I hope, to any, who will impartially conſider what I have written in a Treatiſe called <hi>Conſcience Satisfied in a Cordial and Loyal Submitting to the preſent Government of King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary; and in another ſmall Diſcourſe, in Anſwer to the Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience; and in a Faſt Sermon on <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Art thou for us, or for our Adverſaries?</hi> And I think that the Thankſgiving-days, and the Faſting-days, and the Collects, and Prayers read, and the ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> by all the Members of every Congregation, is a Juſtification of what hath been done in this Revolution, unleſs men are groſs Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and honour God with their mouths, without their hearts.</p>
               <p>And whatever ſome late Biſhops, and Governours of the Church have done, I am ſure the firſt Bleſſed Reformers honoured all Proteſtant Churches as Siſters, and their Divines and Miniſters as Brethren. I know not why <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Arminius</hi> (tho' they differ in ſome Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions) ſhould not all ſtill be honoured as faithful Servants of Chriſt. And here I ſhall produce a few of our Divines, moſt famous, who ſpeak honourably of them; as all men, that hate Faction in the Church ought to do.</p>
               <p>The Reverend Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> (Reply to <hi>Hard. A. Art.</hi> 2. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 6.) ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies <hi>Luther</hi> as a godly man, and accuſeth <hi>Harding</hi> of Slander. And (<hi>Diviſ.</hi> 7) he calls <hi>Melancthon</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> godly learned men. And he calls <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> a moſt worthy and learned Father. (<hi>A.</hi> to <hi>Hardings</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.) And <hi>Harding</hi> commends his Modeſty. And ſurely if Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience had been the Doctrine of thoſe days, and eſteemed (as it hath been of late) Rebellion to oppoſe it, the ever Renowned <hi>Hooker</hi> (Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to Eccl. Pol.) would not have honoured <hi>Calvin</hi> with this <hi>Elogium;</hi> For my own part, I think him (that is, <hi>Calvin</hi>) incomparably the wiſeſt man that ever the French Church did enjoy, ſince the hour it enjoyed him. The Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not wont thus to commend
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95438:22"/>Authors guilty of Hereſie, or Schiſm, or Sedition, or Rebellion. And Dr. <hi>Bilſon</hi> (True difference between Chriſtian Subjection, and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Rebellion, p. 3. pag. 264.) ſaith, <hi>Calvin</hi> is ſo well known to thoſe that be Learned or Wiſe, for his great pains and labours in the Church of God, that a few ſnarling Fryars cannot impeach his Name. And Dr. <hi>Whitgift</hi> againſt the Puritan <hi>T. C.</hi> every where honours <hi>Bullinger, Caſtius,</hi> and more eſpecially <hi>Zuinglius:</hi> And yet all theſe juſtified Defenſive Arms in ſome caſe. Now who are the Innovators? they that follow the firſt Doctors of our Church, or they that have embraced other new and unheard of Principles in Government? I leave the works of our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers to be Judges.</p>
               <p>But here it is objected by ſome weak and factious ſpirits, that our Convention (or Parliament) have done as bad to the late King, as the Rump Parliament, ſo called, <hi>O. C.</hi> and the Army of Sectaries did to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt: And therefore if we are juſtifiable, they are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable, and conſequently <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. ought not to be kept as a day of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and Faſting.</p>
               <p>For this, let the Reader conſider what the Dr. ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 46, 47, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or let him take this Anſwer. Our Cauſe and theirs differ as far as Heaven and Hell, or Good and Bad, Murder and Self-defence. I will not ſay that there were no Corruptions in Government, nor no Innovations brought into the Church: Neither will I diſpute the Reaſonableneſs of the War between the King, and Parliament in the beginning. But ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that the Parliament had ſufficient Cauſe to defend themſelves: Yet,</p>
               <p n="1">1. King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt had given full ſatisfaction to the Two Houſes of Parliament, and the Biſhops, and the Common Prayer were Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law: And all know that it was the National Worſhip, as it is now, and cannot be abrogated, or altered, but by King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: But <hi>O. C.</hi> deſtroyed the Houſe of Lords, and the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer by force, and by the Sword.</p>
               <p n="2">2. King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was a profeſſed Proteſtant, and all his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Miniſters in Church and State were ſuch as the Law allowed: But the Late King was a profeſſed Papiſt, and put Papiſts in Places of Truſt againſt Law, and turned out all the beſt Proteſtants for no reaſon, but only becauſe they oppoſed the Jeſuits and Arbitrary Power.</p>
               <p n="3">3. King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and the Parliament had concluded upon a Settlement to the ſatisfaction of all ſober and wiſe Men in the Kingdom; but <hi>O. C.</hi> and his Army of Sectaries with force turned about a hundred Members out of Parliament, and kept them Priſoners againſt Law and Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>O. C.</hi> and the Sectaries Ruled the Nation by the Sword in time of Peace, contrary to all Law, and Executed many of the moſt Zealous Proteſtants: But King <hi>William</hi> defends all Proteſtants according to Law.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They, like Cruel Tyrants and Uſurpers, deſtroyed the whole
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95438:22"/>Frame of Government, Murdered the King, and Baniſhed all the Royal Family. As there are ſome at this day, who are ſo vain and ſottiſh as to deſire a Common-wealth, and to Root out the Biſhops, and Common Prayer, and ſo bring confuſion into Church and State. As if there were no difference between the Reformation of Abuſes, and deſtroying that which is good and excellent. We ſay that this Faction in a Nation is to be oppoſed as well as the Tyranny and Illegal Proceedings of the Papiſts: For both are deſtructive of our Laws, and Eſtabliſhed Religion. It is true our preſent Buſineſs is againſt the Abominations of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Uſurpations of Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits: But we alſo abhor all thoſe who would Murder a Proteſtant King, and deſtroy our Liberties, and the Religion by Law Eſtabliſhed, and force us contrary to our Conſciences: But King <hi>William</hi> oppoſeth none but Papiſts, who would have deſtroyed us, and he continues our Parliament and our Laws, Liberties, and Religion, with all the Incouragements thereof.</p>
               <p n="6">6. King <hi>William</hi> was invited over by divers of the Nobility, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to ſave us from Popery and Slavery, and was received with the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Joy of Proteſtants: But <hi>O.C.</hi> and his Sectaries, who Barbarouſly and Impudently Murdered King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, were cryed out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by all ſound Proteſtants, who adhered to the Laws of the Nation. So that that Rebellion and King <hi>William</hi>'s Actions, and thoſe that joined with him, differ as much, as Deſtroying a Nation, and Saving a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as the greateſt Sin, and the greateſt Good.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Our Royal Martyr, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt died in the Defence of the Laws, and Eſtabliſhed Religion: But the Late King Abdicated, or Deſerted, or at leaſt went out of the Kingdom, rather than he would Rule according to Law: And when he was gone to <hi>France</hi> the Chief of the Nobility and Gentry deſired the P. of <hi>O.</hi> to take the Government upon him, and to Summon a Convention; which Convention Elected him King, and the Princeſs Queen. The Late King fled, and Baniſhed himſelf, rather than he would do the Nation Juſtice, and when he was gone, the Convention (or Parliament) reſolved to keep him out. The P. of <hi>O.</hi> tho' a Soveraign Prince, and no way Subject to the Late King, did not Murder him, when he had him in his Power: But <hi>O.C.</hi> and the Sectaries of the Army Beheaded King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, tho' he was Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and a Prince of moſt Excellent Virtues, and of Ever Bleſſed Memory.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21, 22. <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change. For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruin of them both?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Text doth not forbid the Change of Government in Abſolute neceſſity, when the Safety of the whole Kingdom requires it, and it is done Regularly, and for the Publick Good. But commands Obedience and Fear to the preſent Lawful King, and never to join with Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, who are reſtleſs under Government, and Lightly, Wantonly, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiouſly,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95438:23"/>or Seditiouſly oppoſe what is preſent. It is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Morally, as if it were Abſolutely evil, and a Sin to change, when the whole Frame of Government is corrupt: But you muſt take it pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially, that a wiſe Man, who fears God, ought not to Change that Form of Government under which he lives, unleſs in urgent neceſſity. But what if the King be given to Change? Then meddle not with Him. Keep the Fundamental Laws and Cuſtoms of your Countrey, and the true Religion by Law Eſtabliſhed. We ſay (ſaith a Learned Author) that if Power be given to the King by Law, yea, or to other Magiſtrates, tho' it be againſt Religion, we have no help but ſuffering, or flying, till we can be helped by Legal ways. But if when we have Laws for our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberties, the King out of his own will, or ſeduced by others, ſhall in an Illegal way ſeek to deprive us of them, now we may defend our ſelves, and in this we reſiſt no Kingly Authority, but the Will of ſuch a Man.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This Text commands Obedience to the King, with all reverence in Heart, Tongue, and Action. But what is this to innocent and lawful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: Which St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and other Schoolmen call <hi>cum moderamine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culpatae tutela.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4. <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned, and done this evil in thy ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Confeſſion of <hi>David</hi> (ſaith a great Divine) is to be taken com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively. He ſinned againſt God alone by way of Excellence; becauſe he could be puniſhed, condemned, and abſolved by God alone. But <hi>David</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo againſt thoſe, who were meer Subjects, as <hi>Bathſheba, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah, Joab,</hi> and <hi>Nathan,</hi> but not as a Tyrant, violating the whole State of the Common-wealth; but as a Sinner, left to his Luſt. Furthermore, no Man could judge of the Perſonal Fact of <hi>David,</hi> except God alone, which pertained not to the Subverſion of the Common-wealth. I ſay, the ſin of <hi>David</hi> was particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, which was not deſtructive to the whole Common-wealth. Beſides, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeedily recanted, and repented of the evil. The ſenſe is, (ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> cited by the Author of the <hi>Synopſis</hi>) as if he ſhould ſay, I do not regard what Men think or ſpeak; if either they ſpare me, or extenuate the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs by flattery, or mitigate my grief with gentle Speeches; yet it is more than enough to me, that I perceive thee my Judge, that Conſcience draws me to thy Tribunal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Other Expoſitors ſay, I have ſinned againſt thee only as a Judge and Avenger, becauſe I can fear puniſhment from thee only. For Kings are free from the bonds of their offences, ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe. R. R.</hi> ſaith, No Creature judgeth the King, but the bleſſed God; otherwiſe he would be King in Name, not in Deed. (G) The Kings ſin is not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Which is all true of the Perſonal Crimes of Princes, or of ſuch Oppreſſions as are ſpeedily repented of.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:95438:23"/>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is true (ſaith one) of Inferiour Magiſtrates as well as Superiors, and yet none will ſay, but the Inferior may be reſiſted. Kings ſhould imitate God in Wiſdom, in Juſtice, in Mercy, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> and defend, not oppreſs the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. To tell a King thus becomes a Prieſt, much better than to delude him with an unaccountable and irreſiſtible Power.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>By me Kings Reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice. By me Princes Rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. By,</hi> here, denotes the Principal cauſe, it doth not exclude the leſs Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, or Inſtrumental, the Election of the People. As, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.29. <hi>By thee</hi> (that is, God) <hi>I have run thro' a Troop;</hi> or by thy help (ſaith <hi>Synop.</hi> out of <hi>G.</hi>) By me as King of Kings Kingdoms are conſtituted; and Perſons ſet over Kingdoms, either are given, or are depoſed according to <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21. &amp; 4.25, 31, 32. and by me they are preſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither doth this forbid the People to defend themſelves againſt a Tyrant, or to Depoſe a Tyrant, but rather acknowledgeth them Inſtruments. This hinders not what St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> ſaith, (2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 10, <hi>art.</hi> 10.) Dominion and Prelacy were introduced by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Right. Becauſe God and Man both concur to Government: God is the firſt Cauſe, Man the ſecond. Whatſoever the ſecond Cauſe doth (ſaith <hi>Forteſcue</hi> out of an ancient Author, <hi>c.</hi> 3.) the ſame doth the firſt Cauſe by an higher and more excellent way or mean.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.31. <hi>A King againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi> And, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is Power; and who may ſay unto him, What doſt thou?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe Texts ſpeak of a King Ruling according to the Cuſtoms and Laws of his Countrey, or not of Tyrants and Oppreſſors: Or, at leaſt, they forbid not ſelf-defence in caſe of Extremity. I may honour the King, and yet not ſuffer him to kill me, when I am innocent, and have ſerved Him faithfully and when he ought by the Laws of God and Man to protect me. <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 30.31. ſpeaks of the glory and happineſs of a potent and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Prince: not of any Moral evil or unlawfulneſs in defending our ſelves againſt Illegal Courſes, Oppreſſion, and Tyranny of wicked Princes. Again, theſe Texts give a General Rule, being wholly ſilent in caſual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions; as in caſe of extream Male-Adminiſtration. The ſacred Writers exclude not certain Pacts, (ſaith a grave Divine) or Laws of Humane Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (or Conſtitution) by which the King is put into that Super-eminency. And the ſaying of <hi>Optatus Milevitanus,</hi> is either to be taken of Emperors or Abſolute Monarchs: or verily of Him, who reſtrains his Super-eminence within the Laws of Divine as well as Humane Conſtitution; for then in truth, There is none above the Emperor, but God alone, who made the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith what may be done, not what may always be rightly done by a Prince. For afterwards, <hi>v.</hi> 9. he teacheth us that many abuſe their Power to Tyranny. <hi>There is a time wherein one Man ruleth over another to his own hurt.</hi> Therefore he doth not give the Magiſtrate leave to do
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95438:24"/>what he will. For the Power of Man is limited by the Word of God, and honeſt Laws. Becauſe it is written, <hi>We muſt obey God rather than Man: and give to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s, and to God the things that are Gods.</hi> The ſecond verſe is not to be underſtood otherwiſe, <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, So obey the King, as rather to obey God, to whom we are all bound with greater Religion.</p>
               <p>Obj. Eccl. 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought; and curſe not the rich in thy bed-chamber; for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Solomon</hi> prohibits reviling, or ſlighting the Kings perſon, or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil of the King, either for natural, or moral, perſonal defects, and vices. And he cautions us againſt wrath for a little Oppreſſion; becauſe a King may eaſily be revenged on us, and ruine us: But he forbids not ſelf-defence in caſe of Univerſal Oppreſſion. If thou art wiſe and skilful, deſpiſe not a young or a fooliſh King, by mocking his Majeſty; by proud ſlandering his Government; by contemning and reproaching his Statutes and Deeds; but (as much as the matter and truth will bear) ſpeak thou honourably of him, and think the beſt, and interpret well actions that are doubtful (ſaith ſome Author.) For it is wiſdom as well as duty to reverence the Kings Perſon and Office, and conceal ſmall miſcarriages.</p>
               <p>Obj. St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. Read the Context, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>Then went the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, and took counſel how they might intangle him in his talk. And they ſent out unto him their Diſciples, with the Herodians, ſaying, Maſter, we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in truth, neither careſt thou for any man, for thou regardeſt not the perſon of men: Tell us therefore, what thinkeſt thou? Is it lawful to give Tribute unto</hi> Caeſar, <hi>or not? But Jeſus perceived their wickedneſs, and ſaid, Why tempt ye me, ye Hypocrites? Shew me the Tribute money; and they brought unto him a penny. And he ſaid unto them, Whoſe is this Image and Superſcription? They ſay unto him,</hi> Caeſars. <hi>Then ſaith he unto them, Bender therefore unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things which are</hi> Caeſars; <hi>and unto God the things that are Gods. When they had heard theſe words, they marvelled, and left him, and went their way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is moſt certain that Tribute is to be paid to our Governours. The Herodians were ſent to intangle him in his talk: And they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded this Queſtion concerning <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Roman Emperor's Tribute. To which our Saviour anſwers, that they ought to render to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars.</hi> So that by Chriſts command all Subjects muſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and chearfully, and for Conſcience ſake render honour, tribute, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, ſubjection, and obedience to the Higher Powers, which are ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God. But what is this to the Deſenſive Arms againſt Tyranny and Oppreſſion? The Jews had promiſed Obedience to the Romans, and to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Now what we promiſe, (Synop. out of G.) tho' forced by neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of War, binds us faſt; for unleſs it were ſo, the whole ſanction of a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95438:24"/>Covenant would periſh. Beſides Poſſeſſion of a long time, which to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to move (or change) is always unjuſt in publick Affairs. Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and the Primitive Chriſtians hearkened to no Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under what ſpecious pretences ſoever, but performed Faith, Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and Obedience to the Emperor. But let any man prove that theſe Emperors did not rule the Jews according to their Promiſe and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and known Laws and Cuſtoms; or that our Saviour forbids defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Lives, Liberties, or Properties, if invaded contrary to Law, Cuſtom, or Covenant. Again, it follows not, that if Chriſt doth not here diſpute <hi>Caeſars</hi> Title, that he never did, nor that his Diſciples never ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied themſelves. I am ſure the Scribes and Phariſees, and the multitude cryed out, when our Saviour was accuſed, <hi>We have no King but</hi> Caeſar; a plain acknowledgment of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Title, Power and Authority.</p>
               <p>Obj. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men; for Kings, and for all that are in Authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and honeſty; for this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This is alſo ſpoken of Governours indefinitely, and of ſuch who would rule according to the Cuſtoms and Laws of their Countries: Not of Tyrants who would Subvert National Laws and Cuſtoms without cauſe. And tho' there was great Confuſions in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire about the Throne, ſometimes yet ſtill the Emperor promiſed to Rule according to Laws and Cuſtoms received. And ſurely no Man can prove that Paſſive O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience was owned in thoſe days, if the Emperor commanded Illegally: Nor was their Hereditary Succeſſion in the Empire. The wickedneſs of Man, cannot deſtroy the Inſtitution of God. But Magiſtrates Kings, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors are conſtituted of God. And Chriſtian Religion doth not overthrow the Political Government of Infidels and Heathens. Therefore we muſt pray for all, Perſecutors, and Idolaters.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Poweers, to obey Magiſtrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All theſe Texts command what no rational Man, much leſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian denieth, ought to be given to our Governors: But they prohibit not Defenſive Arms in caſe of Univerſal Oppreſſion.</p>
               <p>Obj. 1 St. <hi>Pet.</hi> 13, 14, 17. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well. Fear God. Honour the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks indefinitely of Governors, and of Obedience to them; but he ſtates no particular Caſe. When this Epiſtle was written, (<hi>Synop</hi> out of G.) I think that <hi>Claudius,</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> was Emperor. Therefore we muſt obey Infidels, and evil Princes. But this prohibits not Self-defence, when Laws are violated. Tho' the Ordinance or Government in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of its Conſtitution be from Man, (ſaith a Learned Author) yet becauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95438:25"/>of the neceſſity of its Inſtitution, it is from God. Submit to it, tho' of Man, for the Lords ſake. For God is the primary Author. Obſerve Kings and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents are an Humane Conſtitution or Ordinance, made by Men with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Conſent, by certain Laws, yet by the Command and Authority of God. So that I conclude with a great Stateſman, <hi>As it was the Oppreſſion and Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very under which we had been brought, that rendered His Majeſtys undertaking in coming into theſe Kingdoms with armed Force, in order to redeem them, both Honourable and Juſt: So it was the Hope of being delivered by Him from Miſery and Bondage, that incouraged us firſt to invite, and then to cooperate with Him in the Proſecution and Accompliſhment of His Glorious Deſign. It was the Invaſion upon our Laws that we complained of, and from which we deſired and indeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be relieved,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus I have omitted no appearance of an Objection, and have given ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to all, that will examine things impartially and conſcienciouſly, in order to their ready and hearty Obedience to Their Majeſties, and the Preſervation of the Religion, Laws, and Liberties of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude all with a plain Exhortation both in reſpect of the King, and Subjects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, For the King. Seeing His Majeſty hath received Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from God, it concerns him to Adminiſter Juſtice and Judgment. For Gods Eye is All-ſeeing, and he is Omnipreſent. <hi>God ſtandeth in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Mighty: he judgeth among the Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82.1. It is a poor, weak, inferior thing, beneath the Spirit and Dignity of a Prince, to wrong the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: But it is indeed Great and Godlike, to ſeek Judgment, and relieve the Oppreſſed. God hath Honoured Kings with his own Name and Titles, and they ſhould imitate Him in Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Juſtice, and Mercy. And as this tends to the Honour of God, and Happineſs of his Church, and the Proſperity of the Kingdom, ſo it gains the Love and Affection of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which is the only Ambition of Valiant, Wiſe, and Juſt Monarchs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the Subject. Seeing Kings are by Gods Deſignation, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or Conſtitution, let every Subject humbly ſubmit. They derive their Right from the Higheſt Majeſty of Heaven and Earth. They are ſet over us by Gods approbation. And the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who led his People by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> in all Ages hath ſubjected Mankind to ſome of his Viceroys on Earth. And they who are Enemies to them, are Enemies to God, and caſt off that ſweet and eaſie Yoke of Obedience, to which God would have all his ſubmit. This condemns all wilful Offenders, who diſobey Governours. They are in Gods ſtead, and to deſpiſe them, is to deſpiſe God himſelf. And as Subjects ought to yield Obedience to their Soveraigns (which I have Illuſtrated elſewhere) ſo they ought to be grateful for their Favour, Mercy, Clemency, and good Government. And in particular, they ought to be thankful to God, and the King, for the Mercies of this preſent time, even the Reviving of our Religion, Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
